<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A box of spikenard newly broken not so much for the preparation of the burial; as for the clearer illustration, and exornation of the birth and nativity of our blessed Lord and Saviour Christ Jesus. Contained in a short and sweet discourse which was at first hinted, and occasioned through a question propounded by R.B.P. de K. Which is now answered and resloved by T.M. P. de P.</title>
            <author>Malpas, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2140_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 243:E2140[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A box of spikenard newly broken not so much for the preparation of the burial; as for the clearer illustration, and exornation of the birth and nativity of our blessed Lord and Saviour Christ Jesus. Contained in a short and sweet discourse which was at first hinted, and occasioned through a question propounded by R.B.P. de K. Which is now answered and resloved by T.M. P. de P.</title>
                  <author>Malpas, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.S. for George Sawbridge, and are to be sold ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.M. = Thomas Malpas.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novem. Nouem:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Nativity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BOX OF SPIKENARD Newly Broken.</p>
            <p>Not ſo much for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Burial; as for the clearer Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Exornation of the Birth and Nativity of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>CONTAINED In a ſhort and ſweet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe which was at firſt hinted, and occaſioned through a Queſtion propounded by <hi>R.B.P. de K.</hi> Which is now anſwered and reſolved by <hi>T.M. P. de P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl> While the King ſiteth at his Table, my Spikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.</hi> S. for <hi>George Sawbridge,</hi> and are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE Indifferent and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Shall uſe no further Preface or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to this inſuing Treatiſe, but onely to acquaint thee, that this Task was at firſt undertaken by me, not onely for the ſatisfaction of ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intimate Friends and honeſt-minded Proteſtants, who did much ſollicite and intreat me hereunto; but alſo for the confutation of all ſuch peeviſh and perverſe oppoſers of the Truth. And to ſtop the mouthes (if it were poſſible) of ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Antilegons, Antagoniſts and
<pb facs="tcp:119631:3"/>Gain-ſayers; who do much grieve and offend their weak Brethren, by putting a ſtumbling block, or an occaſion to fall in their way; even touching things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and matters of little or no conſequence at all.
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> Such men as theſe you know are cenſured and perſtringed by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> And I know, alſo that by the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> they are condemned, <hi>Levit. 19.14.</hi> Thou ſhalt not curſe the deaf, nor put a ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling-block before the blind, but ſhalt fear thy God; I am the Lord. As for ſuch quaint and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, difficult and preciſe Readers as theſe, I care not how few theſe poor labours of mine do meet with: I know they will be apt, like <hi>Zoilus,</hi> to look upon them, <hi>fronte corrugante,</hi> with a wrinkled or bended brow; and, with <hi>Momus,</hi> not onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite the lipp at them, but, <hi>cum dente Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino,</hi> gnaſh with their malicious teeth, and be ready to rent and tear them in pieces; I know that they will be apt to ſay, that I am become a fool in print, and am very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to blaze my own folly and foppery; yea, and to maintain my old Popery and Superstition; yea, perhaps, they will call me and accuſe me; as <hi>Tertullus</hi> did <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.5.</note> to be a peſtilent fellow, and a mover of ſedition, and an enemy to the State,
<pb facs="tcp:119631:3"/>with the like obloquies and exprobrations: But when I meet with ſuch as theſe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put on <hi>Paul's</hi> reſolution, and ſay, 1 Cor. <hi>3.4. with me it is a very ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged of them, or of man's Judgment;</hi> yea, I judge not mine own ſelf, for I know nothing of my ſelfe: <hi>(i. e.)</hi> whereof to boast, ſaving of mine infirmities, (as he ſpeaks elſewhere): yet put the caſe I ſhould know any thing in my ſelf that is commendable or praiſe-worthy, yet am I not hereby juſtified; but he that judgeth me is the Lord: <hi>Quod olim altè &amp; acutè quiſpiam, id hîc verâ voce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamo: Satis mihi pauci lectores, ſatis eſt unus, ſatis eſt nullus: id tamen peto, ut quicunque haec tangens cognoſcendi animum adferat, &amp; ſimul ignoſcendi; namque vetus &amp; verum proverbium eſt, Ut facilius eſt carpere quám corrigere, ſic facilius eſt interrogare quam reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> We have in theſe laſt and worst times, in theſe perillous and pernicious, dangerous and Climacterical days of ours a new brood of thoſe old Serpents, a freſh generation of Vipers lately hatched and ſprung forth amongſt us, as it were a ſpawn of thoſe proud and inſolent and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percilious Scribes and Phariſees that
<pb facs="tcp:119631:4"/>were amongſt the Jews, who vilifie Chriſt, and do both ſcornfully and diſdainfully think and ſpeak of Him, as they did, Mark <hi>6.3. Is not this the Carpenter, the Son of</hi> Mary, <hi>the Brother of</hi> James, <hi>and</hi> Joſes, <hi>and</hi> Juda, <hi>and</hi> Simon? and are not his Siſters here with us? And they were offended at him. And how truly did that old good man <hi>Simeon</hi> Propheſie of Him; ſaying, <hi>Behold, this Child is ſet for the Fall and Riſing again of many in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and for a Signe that ſhall be ſpoken againſt:</hi> Neither is it without a Myſtery which the Angel told the Shepheards. This ſhall be a ſigne unto you; you ſhall find the Infant wrapt in ſwadling Clothes: Upon which word, devout <hi>Bernard</hi> deſcants ſweetly thus, <hi>In ſignum poſiti ſunt panni tui (ô bone Jeſû); ſed, in ſignum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſigne that is ſpoken againſt, a ſigne that is done againſt; for we cannot abide thy Clouts, nor thy Raggs (O Lord Jeſu), nor any part of thy Humility: which makes the Proud and Arrogant, and inſolent ſpirits of a late up ſtart Phantaſtical and Pharaiſaicall Generation; ſo peremptorily and perverſly to ſpeak, and audaciouſly
<pb facs="tcp:119631:4"/>to write, againſt the ſolemn Remembrance of thy Nativity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> to ſhew their frenzy and madneſs I have written, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to divulge theſe Papers, and if thou doſt receive any comfort or profit by theſe poor labours of mine, give God the Glory, and wiſh well to him, Who wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing but well to thee in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> Appendix to the Preface.</head>
            <p>THere are two things principally required in a Miniſter, the one that he be able to exhort with whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Doctrine: the other that he hath skill to Improve them that ſay againſt it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9. whereunto agreeth that witty ſaying of grave St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that he muſt be <hi>veritatis propugnator, &amp; erroris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnator,</hi> (i.e.) he muſt be a maintainer of the Truth, and a withſtander of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Auguſt, de doctrinâ Chriſti.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:5"/>
            <head>Author ad Libellum.</head>
            <head type="sub">Vade ſed incultus,—</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Candidus Auctoris Amicus, ad Lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem candidum et benevolum.</head>
               <l>REad on good <hi>Reader</hi> but read aright;</l>
               <l>Do not miſtake, nor conſtrue things in spight.</l>
               <l>'Tis a proud word to ſpeak yet true I ween,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a Book as this you have ſeldom ſeen.</l>
               <l>All Books this <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> whereon vain men do look,</l>
               <l>Are not to be compared to this Little Book.</l>
               <l>You cannot play at a more delightſome Game,</l>
               <l>Than to handle, and peruſe, and read the ſame.</l>
               <l>'Tis not <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, here is no ill;</l>
               <l>Be not afraid, but open't with goodwill.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:6"/>
               <l>'Tis rather <hi>Mary</hi>'s Box, ſhe brake in love</l>
               <l>Of her dear Saviour, as't did truly prove;</l>
               <l>An Ointment 'twas, ſo pretious and ſo ſweet,</l>
               <l>It did perfume the Houſe where they did meet:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spikenard</hi> the ſame was call'd, and ſo it was,</l>
               <l>For it did other Odours far ſurpaſs.</l>
               <l>So if this <hi>Spikenard</hi> ſhall afford a pleaſing ſmell,</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Readers</hi> (I wis) ſhall pleaſe us paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing well.</l>
               <l>It is not for his Burial but his Birth,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe He was born for to redeem the Earth;</l>
               <l>Other wiſe we had all been cast to Hell,</l>
               <l>With the Devil and his Angels there to dwell.</l>
               <l>O happy time! that ever He was born,</l>
               <l>To ſave poor Sinners that were thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn.</l>
               <l>To celebrate the five and twentieth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O let us all, with one accord, remember,</l>
               <l>And not forget His kindneſs towards Man,</l>
               <l>But ſet forth's praiſe with all the Might we can.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:6"/>
               <l>Did not the Augels do the ſame, and ſing</l>
               <l>A holy Carroll to our Heavenly King?</l>
               <l>Did not the Shepherds &amp; Wiſe men of the Eaſt</l>
               <l>Praiſe Him, &amp; bring preſents of the beſt;</l>
               <l>Even Gold, &amp; Frankincenſe, &amp; Myrrhe?</l>
               <l>To come ſo far they did them ſelves beſtir;</l>
               <l>In ſo ſhort a time (I mean) to come ſo far:</l>
               <l>But they were guided by a glorious Star</l>
               <l>To <hi>Bethlem</hi> Town, and to that very place</l>
               <l>Wherein that bleſſed Babe lay-full of grace,</l>
               <l>Though mean in ſhew, and laid but in a Manger,</l>
               <l>Yet they acknowledg'd him, though they were ſtrangers;</l>
               <l>And down they fell upon their bended knee,</l>
               <l>And aid adore and worſhip him, all three;</l>
               <l>Opening their Treaſures, &amp; offering ſuch a thing</l>
               <l>As did become a Man, a God, a King:</l>
               <l>A Myſtery! for Myrrhe, &amp; Frankincenſe, &amp; Gold</l>
               <l>Do ſignify the Office of <hi>Chriſt</hi> threefold:</l>
               <l>For both King, Prieſt, &amp; Prophet's He</l>
               <l>To rule, &amp; pray for, &amp; teach both thee &amp; me.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:7"/>
            <p>And this, according to the Chriſtian Poet <hi>Juvencus,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Aurum, Thus, Myrrham, Regi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Homini<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Dona ferunt.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="book_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:7"/>
            <head>Liber ad Lectorem.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Si Natura negat, facit Indignatio Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</head>
               <l>AND is it News you look for? O <hi>Sir,</hi> There's none;</l>
               <l>I do but tell you of a thing done long agone:</l>
               <l>Yet this is News, for me-thinks 'tis very ſtrange</l>
               <l>To hear of ſuch an uncouth, &amp; prodigious Change,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> ſhould be buried! Is old <hi>England</hi> dead?</l>
               <l>Alas! This whimzy comes from a ſtrange head,</l>
               <l>Who would have all things new, in spight of old.</l>
               <l>Sure they would have a new <hi>Chriſt</hi> if they could;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:8"/>
               <l>A <hi>Chriſt</hi> without a Birth: How ſtrange is this?</l>
               <l>Sure they are madd, or elſe they dote, I wis:</l>
               <l>New Lords, new Laws: What, would they have new Gods?</l>
               <l>Or do they long to be ſcourg'd with new Rods.</l>
               <l>War was in the Gates, und many a miſery moe,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iſrael</hi> did the living God foregoe,</l>
               <l>To worſhip dead Idols of wood and stone,</l>
               <l>Whereas they ſhould have worſhipt God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</l>
               <l>But mark their reaſon, which is not worth a ruſh,</l>
               <l>They all want ſhame, or elſe they would bluſh;</l>
               <l>Becauſe they know not when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born,</l>
               <l>Therefore, like <hi>Jews,</hi> at's Birth they ſcorn;</l>
               <l>And ſcoff at us, becauſe that we do dance</l>
               <l>Before the Ark, &amp; do <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Name ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance:</l>
               <l>But let them <hi>Michol</hi>-like diſdain, yet we</l>
               <l>With holy <hi>David,</hi> will yet viler be.</l>
               <l>The Article of his Birth-day they do deny</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Tenet's I defy:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:8"/>
               <l>For born he was, and of a Virgin pure,</l>
               <l>And did for us the pains of Hell endure,</l>
               <l>To bring us unto happineſs, and perfect bliſs,</l>
               <l>Wherein no ſenſe of grief nor ſorrow is.</l>
               <l>Then cauſe have we for to obſerve this time,</l>
               <l>And not to account it any fault or crime:</l>
               <l>This Feaſt of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath been highly kept of yore,</l>
               <l>And never yet eſteemed Popery before.</l>
               <l>It is not Superſtition to eat a Pye;</l>
               <l>Sure, he that tells you this, tells you a Lye,</l>
               <l>And doth diſſemble with his glozing tongue.</l>
               <l>Theſe Round head Hypocrites do all the wrong:</l>
               <l>All ancient customes be they ne're ſo good,</l>
               <l>They esteem no more than Tales of <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin-hood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Cauſe Papiſts keep it, therefore muſt not we?</l>
               <l>'Cauſe they are good to the poor wee'l hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded be.</l>
               <l>Oh no! Not ſo, my Maſters, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver betide,</l>
               <l>Let us follow the Scripture for our onely Guide,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:9"/>
               <l>Which tells us, <hi>'Tis better to give than to receive;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And he that ſaith not ſo, doth us deceive.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reader</hi> farewell, I do defy</l>
               <l>All thoſe which <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Birth-day deny.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:9"/>
            <head>To his Loving Friend Mr. <hi>T. M.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being my hap, not long ſince, to find this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Yours, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the printing and publiſhing thereof, in a Friend's Houſe; And being, upon Inquiry, informed touching the Quality of the Authour, I wondred what man it was, that had ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Courage in him, as to adventure to vindicate this Chriſtian Duty of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the Nativity of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> contemning the clamorous Cenſures, and the vain Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections,
<pb facs="tcp:119631:10"/>and <hi>Argumenta mutilata</hi> of the weak multitude of Pretenders to Religion and Learning. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much affected with your Chriſtian valour, in this kind, and deſirous to commend the ſame to poſterity; It is not in my power to do it more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, than by adding this Epiſtle to your Treatiſe, which (if I were eloquent) I ſhould commend in the Superlative de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. For, although the valiant and learned Champions, or rather railing Antagoniſts, of our times, <hi>evemunt quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in buccam venit,</hi> and ſpit out their venome againſt it, and ſtrive, <hi>tanquam pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> to maintain that it is a meer vanity to obſerve the bleſſed time of Chriſt's Birth-day: Yet, if they will give me leave to ſpeak, I ſhall tell them, That the moſt learned Arguments that their ſubtle brains can invent or produce, are not ſufficient to prove it a Sin, to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate this time; and beſides, I will tell them, it is an <hi>Herculean</hi> labour, and as hard a task as to fetch <hi>Cerberus</hi> out of Hell. And although they give out the worſt words they can rake out of the ſink of their rotten brains, againſt it; yet I will tell them, It is eaſier for them to
<pb facs="tcp:119631:10"/>drive a Spunge into a Milſtone, than to diſſwade many godly People from the due Obſervation of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Whoever thou art, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in thy ſelf, That the bonouring of this time is juſt, honeſt, commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, good, and lawful. And I prove it thus, with a threefold Argument (and you know that a Cord which is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, or thrice doubled, is not eaſily broken): My Argument is this,</p>
            <p>That which God, and the Church of God, and the ancient Fathers have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be kept and celebrated, ought to be kept and celebrated; and the uſe of it, is good, pious, lawful, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable:</p>
            <p>But God, and the Church of God, and the Fathers, have commanded this day to be kept and celebrated. <hi>Ergo.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I prove that God hath commanded it out of <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And again, when he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the firſt-begotten into the World, he ſaith, <hi>And let all the Angels of God worſhip Him,</hi> Pſal. 77.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Incurvate vos ei
<pb facs="tcp:119631:11"/>omnes Divi.</hi> Luke <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>And the Angel ſaid unto them, Fear not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That the Church of God, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, commanded it to be celebrated, is exactly proved in the Anſwers of ſome of the 14 <hi>Arguments,</hi> and I need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them here: And I do believe that there is no man in this Nation, who hath lived forty or fifty years, but hath known <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> — day ſtrictly obſerved and kept.</p>
            <p>But alas! We can expect no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if we caſt but our eyes upon the age wherein we live. It is moſt admirably deciphered by the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>De duro eſt Ultima ferro;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Protinus irrupit venae pejoris in aevum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omne nefas: Fugêre Pudor, Verum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, Fideſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In quorum ſubiêre locum frandeſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſidiae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp; vis, &amp; amor ſceleratus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119631:11"/>
                  <l>At laſt the Iron-Age comes bluſtring in,</l>
                  <l>I'ch' latter times, and fills the World with Sin;</l>
                  <l>All Shame, and Truth, and Faithfulneſſe are gone:</l>
                  <l>Fraud and Deceipt, Lords paramount, alone,</l>
                  <l>Do rule: By ſnares and violence men get</l>
                  <l>Eſtates, and all is Fiſh that comes to Net.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which how truly it is verified, every body may ſee, if not as blind as Moles; and may feel, if not ſenſleſſe. I ſhall now ſpeak a word or two to ſome which raile at, and preach down, the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Time: &amp; deſire them to ſpend the time which they ſpend in burying Antiquity and lawful Cuſtoms, in the Tranſlating of many things which are not as yet tranſlated, and not to mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polize Knowledge. I will name ſome places which are not as yet tranſlated, <hi>viz. Pſal.</hi> 56. To the Chief Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Why could not they have tranſlated it <hi>Super Columbam mutam remotis,</hi> The dumb Dove in a far Country. And I
<pb facs="tcp:119631:12"/>am perſwaded, that they durſt not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate one Word, when they looked on their own Coats, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4. <hi>I will cut off the names of the</hi> CHEMARIMS <hi>with the Prieſts;</hi> meeting with the Word, now and then, in <hi>Hoſea,</hi> they tranſlated it <hi>Priests;</hi> but here it being joyned with the word <hi>PRIEST,</hi> my Blades plaid the honeſt (I ſhould have ſaid, the ſelfiſh) men, and never tranſlated it at all: <hi>Tremelius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> give it a very honeſt and true Verſion, <hi>Nomen Atrato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cum Sacerdotibus,</hi> The Names of Black-Coats with the Prieſts. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this Scripture to the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of our Rigid <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> and when they look upon it, let them do as the Peacock doth, when he looks on his leggs.</p>
            <p>I deſire the Reader of this Book, not to give credit to every one that ſpeaks againſt Antiquity, nor to carp at that which they cannot mend: for I dare ſay, and will affirm, that the Authour here of hath written herein, nothing but what is true, nothing contrary to the Will of God; to whoſe Protection I leave him.</p>
            <p>The Almighty bleſs him, &amp; proſper his ſtudies: For ſuch is the deſire and hopes
<pb facs="tcp:119631:12"/>of him, who craves leave to ſubſcribe himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant and true admirer of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Ingenuity, Sincerity, and Courage. T. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:13"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>MAny of our late Divines bring ſuch poor weak Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Celebration of Chriſt's birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, that I am almoſt aſhamed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat any of them; much leſs then, will I trouble my ſelf to anſwer them, they being ſo ridiculous, that (if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) they would cauſe <hi>corpus rationis vacuum,</hi> to laugh them to ſcorne. Two or three I will repeat: the firſt is of a Divine that brought a <hi>Rubrick</hi> or <hi>Almanack</hi> into the Pulpit to bury this Day, and reads Arguments out of it to the People, and tells them a tale of a rub without a bottome; I am ſure this Gentleman might have looked in a <hi>Jack-Dawes</hi> Neſt, and have found as good Arguments there, as any he found in his <hi>Almanack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Divine ſaith, It is not onely a bad time, but it is the worſt of all times; and thinks, This <hi>ignis fatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119631:13"/>of his giddy brain, is ſufficient to lead men from the Truth; But Alas! I will be ſo bold as to deny his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and I am ſure, he cannot prove it, for he hath no more skill in arguing, then a Cow hath in dancing.</p>
            <p>The third Divine ſaith, It is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's day, and therefore ought to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and never to be celebrated. But I reply thus: His Body will deſcend into <hi>Orcus,</hi> and his Name will be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in Oblivion, long before this Day will be buryed: for I doubt not, but it will be celebrated as it ought to be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till there will be a period put unto all things. I wiſh all Chriſtian Readers of this Book, happineſs in this World, and a Crown of Glory in that to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119631:14"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119631:14"/>
            <head>A BOX OF Spikenard <hi>Newly Broken.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Queſtion propounded by <hi>Richard B.</hi> which was the occaſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>WHether the Nativity of Chriſt, commonly called Chriſtmas-day, ought to be celebrated;</hi> R. B. <hi>denyeth it, and endeavours to prove the contrary. His Arguments are theſe</hi> 14 <hi>following.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119631:15"/>
               <p>Arg. 1. <hi>There is nothing in the World a Duty, which God hath not made a Duty; But God never made this a Duty:</hi> Ergo, <hi>it is no Duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 2. <hi>If I ſhould obſerve this Day, I am afraid leſt I ſhould deny the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 3. <hi>I am fearful leſt by doing ſo, I ſhould arrogate the making of a Day to my ſelf: for if I ſhould do ſo much as in me lyeth, I ſhould make a Day to my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 4. <hi>I am fearful leſt by ſo doing, I ſhould ſet up a Day againſt God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 5. <hi>It is the Devil's policy to imitate God, and when he will be holy, he will be holyer then God; and when he ſeeth God will have a Sabbath to be kept, then he will ſet up a Day, and he will have a Chriſtmas Day to be kept, and he will have his Pictures in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>windows, and the Croſſe made on the Childrens foreheads in Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119631:15"/>
               <p>Arg. 6. <hi>I am fearful, leſt I ſhould be condemned for accuſing God for want of Wiſdom, and ſo make my ſelf wiſer then God, as though he knew not what ſhould be done as well as I, and ſo derogate from the Wiſdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 7. <hi>I am fearful of being more inexcuſable for my ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 8. <hi>It ſeemeth to me a vain and needleſſe thing, Firſt, becauſe God hath ſet apart a Sabbath, the Lords Day, for this purpoſe to meditate upon God's love in redeeming the World; Secondly, Becauſe I never heard a good Argument for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 9. <hi>It is an impoſſibility to keep it, and God never made an impoſſibility, a duty: no man knoweth certainly on which day Christ was born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 10. <hi>I obſerve God hides things purpoſely from us, to ſee whether we will do any thing on our own heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 11. <hi>It hath not bin the practiſe of Chriſtian Churches to obſerve it?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119631:16"/>
               <p>Arg. 12. <hi>In all doubtfull Caſes a man ought to go on the ſureſt ſide: Now I am ſure, It is no ſin not to keep it, but am not ſure, It is no ſin to keep it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 13. <hi>This time ought not to be celebrated; for there is more ſin commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in theſe</hi> 12 <hi>Dayes, then is in all the year after, in Drunkenneſſe, Gluttony,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Arg. 14. <hi>God bleſſeth his own Day, the Sabbath, but hath not bleſſed this, with ſucceſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here followeth the Anſwer of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas M.</hi> to the forerecited Queſtions and Arguments: and herein, the honour of Chriſt his Nativity is Vindicated, or the Solemnity of his Birth-day (which is commonly called <hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi>), avowed and averred, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> juſtified and maintained to be lawful and good: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this Anſwer to fourteen arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Arguments, or weak Linſey-Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy Reaſons, which have been of late eventilated, and divulged in writing to the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119631:16"/>
               <head>Anſwer to the firſt Argument.</head>
               <p>You may remember that the firſt Argument runneth thus; <hi>There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World a duty which God hath not made a duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But God never made the Celebration of the Nativity of Chriſt a Duty, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is no Duty.</p>
               <p>Though this Argument is Scholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and Syllogiſtically propounded, yet I ſhall be ſo bold as to deny the Minor or ſecond propoſition, and that for theſe Reaſons: for although it be not in words plainly expreſſed, yet in ſenſe it is ſignificantly and ſufficiently implyed, and, by way of neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, may be deduced and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> at the 6. <hi>Verſe.</hi> When he bringeth forth his firſt begotten Son into the World, He ſaith, <hi>And let all the Angels of Gods worſhip him;</hi> and for proof hereof, to ſhew the ſweet harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and conſent of both Teſtaments, the Old and the New, and that one and the ſame Spirit ſpeaks in both: For the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119631:17"/>ſame God is Author of both, and the ſame Chriſt is Subject of both; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that each Teſtament is in other: for in the Law there is an hidden Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and in the Goſpel a revealed Law; <hi>Being like the two Cherubius on the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-Seat, whoſe faces looked one towards the other,</hi> Exod. 15.20. St. <hi>Paul</hi> alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. And howſoever the ordinary reading of the Pſalm is, <hi>worſhip Him all ye gods;</hi> yet the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Interprets it of Angels directly, ſaying according as <hi>Tremelius</hi> renders it out of the Original, <hi>Incurvanto ſe, bonorem exhibentes ei, omnes Angeli;</hi> Let all the Angels of God worſhip Him: For ſo we find it to be true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and ſo it was at Chriſt's Birth, and upon the very Day of his Nativity; That one Angel firſt reports it to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> and many other of thoſe Celeſtial Choriſters ſing Praiſes to God for it; Fear not, ſaid <hi>Gabriel, for Behold, I bring you good tydings of great joy, which ſhall be unto all Nations; For unto you is born this Day in the City of</hi> David, <hi>a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord; and ſuddenly there was with the Angel a multitude of the Heavenly Hoſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119631:17"/>prayſing God,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>Gloria Deo in Excelſis,</hi> &amp;c. Luke 2.13.14. Now I inferr from hence, that theſe Angels came not about this Errand without ſome ſpecial Commiſſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, and therefore it was a Duty Commanded and Given in charge to them; Now, if the Angels for whom Chriſt came not, were to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it; How much more ought we Men to obſerve it, for whoſe ſake, and for whoſe Salvation he was Incarnate, and became Man; for verily, He took not on Him, <hi>Naturam Angelorum, ſed Semen Abrahami,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> not the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">Dubartas.</note> Wherefore the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, As they are called by a Divine Poet, The ſacred Tutors of the Saints, and the guard of God's Elect, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> So they may alſo be called Tutors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors to us, to inſtruct and teach us this Leſſon, and may be alſo exemplary Patterns and Precedents to us, in the practiſe and performance of this Duty. Anſwerable and agreeable hereunto, is the plat-form of our grand Maſter, and bleſſed Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus; who hath taught us in the third Petition
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119631:18"/>of that his moſt abſolute and perfect Prayer, to pray thus, <hi>Thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven:</hi> wherein we are taught to pray, (as all the beſt Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxal Divines do expound it), that the will of God may be obeyed, and done by us as Chearfully, Speedily, Faithfully, Conſtantly and Continually: as it is done by the Angels in Heaven. And therefore as the Angels melodiouſly chanted it here on Earth at the Birth of Chriſt: So let us likewiſe unanimouſly celebrate, &amp; ſet forth his praiſe, and ſay, <hi>Glory be to God on High, in Earth Peace, good will towards Men. We bleſſe Thee, we praiſe Thee, we glorifie Thee, we give thanks to Thee for thy great Glory.</hi> Theſe words were at firſt added to the Heavenly Carroll of the Holy Angels, by that famous Biſhop <hi>Hilary,</hi> and uſed by him in his own Church, <hi>Anno</hi> 340. So ſaith <hi>Caſſander's Litturgy, Cap.</hi> 22. And that this is a Duty expected and required from us, upon good ground, and ſpecial Reaſons and Cauſes that ſhould move us hereunto, grave St. <hi>Austin</hi> tells us wittily, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly, This Quaery hath a ſufficient Quaery, <hi>Quia verbum caro factum eſt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119631:18"/>&amp; habitavit intra nos,</hi> Becauſe the Word was made fleſh, and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, <hi>&amp; vidimus Gloriam,</hi> and we faw his Glory (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>as of the onely begotten of the Father, full of Grace and Truth,</hi> John 1.14. Wherefore as thoſe <hi>Perſian</hi> Sages (who were both Wiſemen and Kings) being led by the guidance, and aſſiſtance, and direction of a Starr to the place of Chriſt's Birth, and there did adore and worſhip Him, and preſented gifts unto Him, Gold, Frankincenſe, and Myrrh, <hi>Math.</hi> 2.10. and this their coming made to the greater condemnation of the Jews, and to ſhame their blockiſhneſs and blindneſs, their ſluggiſhneſs carnality and infidelity, who ſtanding hard-by, ſaw not ſo much as they who came from far, according to that ſpeech of <hi>Leo, Veritas illuminat magos, Infidelitas obcoecat magistros:</hi> So it is to be feared, leſt the Lord for our contempt of Chriſt, and the unſpeakable benefits that we have received by his firſt coming in the fleſh, leſt the Lord (I ſay) for our ingratitude, and for our careleſſeneſſe and carnality, take his Word from us Chriſtians, as he did his King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119631:19"/>the Jews, and give it to ſuch as we think to be moſt alien from God and his Goſpel, even to <hi>Moors,</hi> and <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Infidells,</hi> who perhaps may bring forth better fruits of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Thankfulneſs than we have done and ſo riſe up in Judgment at the latter day, and condemn us; for if wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, brought up in Gentiliſm and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, come to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and believe, what excuſe then belongs to the Jews? So if Infidels and Pagans believe and obey, What ſhall become of us, Chriſtians, who want both Faith and Obedience? Thus much for the anſwering of the firſt Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the ſecond Argument.</head>
               <p>The Words of the ſecond Argument are theſe, <hi>If I ſhould obſerve this day, I am fearfull leſt I ſhould deny the Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Scripture; for in the Scripture all things are contained which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation, and all things which are needfull to be believed, and done by a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, for the attainment of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> But the Celebration of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Nativity is not contained therein; <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119631:19"/>If I ſhould obſerve this, I ſhould deny the Perfection of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That the Article of our Faith, touching <hi>Christ</hi>'s Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Manifeſtation in the Fleſh, is both commended, and commanded, in the Scripture; and I refer you or any other indifferent Man, not onely to our Apoſtolicall Creed, which, although it be not Protocanonical Scripture, yet (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks) it is the Key of the Scripture, and (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> terms it) a plain, ſhort, abſolute, ſumm of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith: It is indeed a ſweet and brief <hi>Compendium</hi> and Abridgment of the whole Goſpel: But alſo I referr you to the learned and authentick Creed of judicious <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> (which is an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and compleat Expoſition of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer;) who ſaith, <hi>Quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vult ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> &amp;c. Whoſoever will be ſaved, it is neceſſary to his everlaſting Salvation, That he believe rightly in the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ:</hi> For the right Faith is, That we believe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Son of God, is God and Man: And when did He become Man? or when was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119631:20"/>God manifeſted in the Fleſh, but on this day? And what fitter day can there be, to confeſs this Faith, than on the very ſame day he was born? For this is to perform, <hi>Opus diei in die ſuo.</hi> And this hath been both done and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, or allowed of, alſo to be done, by as ancient, learned, godly, and zealous Doctors and Divines, as ever the whole Chriſtian World affoarded, ſince the firſt appearance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the ſhape of Man; even by thoſe <hi>Chariots &amp; Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of</hi> Iſrael, who were the chief Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and reſplendent Lights of the times, the Glory of the Churches, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diamonds, Pearls, and Ornaments, of the places where they lived, men fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and renowned in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; namely, St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, Baſil, Cyril, Beda, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact, Euthymius, Ludolphus, Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Homilies, and Orations, for this day's Solemnity, are both extant and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent: and might be made alſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and apparant (if need were), ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to convince and ſtop the mouth of any peeviſh and perverſe Antagoniſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119631:20"/>or Gainſayer whatſoever. To theſe we may add (<hi>Dia Poemata</hi>) the Divine Poems of thoſe ſweet, mellifluous, Chriſtian Poets, <hi>Palladius</hi> and <hi>Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> made in an honourable memoriall of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour's Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity: And what if we mentioned here the rate Prophecies and Praedictious of the <hi>Sybillaes</hi> of old, who foretold us of theſe things; and the very Heroicall Verſes, and ſtately <hi>Genethliacon</hi>'s of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Poets, who lived both before ſome of them, and otherſome alſo about the time of the Birth of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Raptures and Enthuſiaſms, not onely from <hi>Sybilla</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> but as ſome think, and are bold to conjecture it, from the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>This was it that made <hi>Virgil</hi> to raiſe up his Muſe to a higher ſtrain, <hi>Eclog.</hi> 4.
<q>
                     <l>Sicelides Muſae, paulo majora cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</l>
                     <l>Jam redit &amp; Virgo, redeunt Saturnia Regna,</l>
                     <l>Jam nova Progenies coelo dimittitur alto:</l>
                     <l>Aspice, venturo laetentur ut omnia ſê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clo.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119631:21"/>For now return the daies of Peace, now the new Progeny is ſent from Heaven; behold, all things ſhall then rejoyce and be glad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tully,</hi> in <hi>Lib. Divinationis,</hi> gives this Obſervation out of <hi>Sybil,</hi> that ſhe propheſyeth of a King to come, <hi>Quem Regem colere debemus, ſi velimus eſſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi;</hi> which King we muſt worſhip if we would be ſaved. And this King ſhould aboliſh all falſe Religions whatſoever. Now concerning all theſe, if you ſhould cavill and object againſt them, or any of them, and ſay, What is this to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Then will I anſwer you, as our Saviour anſwered the Phariſees, finding fault with his Diſciples, for their cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hoſanna before him, when he ridd into <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> I tell you, that if theſe ſhould have held their peace, the very ſtones would cry out and applaud Him. Well then, Have all theſe doted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lired in their writing concerning this thing, namely, the ſolemn Obſervation of this high and feſtival Time, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the World's moſt gracious, and glorious, and bleſſed Redeemer? and are you the onely wiſe man (as it were) that is now left upon the Earth, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119631:21"/>them and direct us? have all theſe erred? Even ſo will we. And more ſweet ſhall our Errour be unto us with theſe, (I ſpeak eſpecially of thoſe ancient and reverend Fathers of the Primitive Church, whom I named before,) who, I dare ſay, were all, and every one of them, as fearful to offend God, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Perfection of the Scriptures, as you for the very life can poſſibly be; more ſweet, I ſay, ſhall our errour be unto us, with theſe, of whom we make no queſtion, but that they are all bound up in the bundle of life, with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the firſt-born, than a new and recent device and purpoſe, of bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Anniverſary remembrance of this day, in the ſilent Night, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Grave of everlaſting Oblivion, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded unto us by you, and ſuch as you, who take upon them to be the grand Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of theſe times, and great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers, and principal Innovators, of all ancient, lawful, and laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes whatſoever. Let others affect Novelty how they pleaſe; for my own part, I ever reverenced and admired Antiquity, eſpecially when I have found it in the way of Verity; and If I were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119631:22"/>worthy to admoniſh our young, upſtart, malapert, Maſters of theſe times, I would wiſh them to remember what grave St. <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith in his 118 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. &amp; cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Ipſa mutatio conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, etiam quâ adjuvat utilitate, pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat novitate.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answer">
               <head>Auſwer to the third Argument.</head>
               <p>The words of the third Argument are theſe, <hi>I am fearfull leſt I ſhould make a day to my ſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> I wonder whether your Lecture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day is not a day made to your ſelf? I doubt not but you have done as much as in you lyeth concerning your Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture-day, and both extoll and preferr it before the day of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Birth; For this day hapning, not long ſince, to be upon your Lecture-day, you did not ſpare to ſpeak it, nor bluſh to give it out in the Pulpit, (as I was credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſome that heard you;) That if that day had not hapned on your Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture-day, you had not then preached; ſo that your day, muſt by all means, be obſerved and kept ſtrictly and praeciſely, but our Saviour's day muſt be ſcornfully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119631:22"/>ſlighted and neglected, as a day not ſcarce fit to be named, much leſs to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated and regarded with honour. But I ſay, Let his Birth-day be celebrated, yea, all praiſe and Glory be unto him, who was born and died for our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the fourth Argument.</head>
               <p>The fourth Argument is this, <hi>I am fearfull, leſt by obſerving this day, I ſhould ſet up a day against God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, If you obſerve and celebrate this day, you ſet not a day up againſt God, but for God: for that which you do for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> you do for God, for we know that God and <hi>Christ</hi> are not divided, but He and the Father are One, they are his own words, <hi>John</hi> 10.30. <hi>Ego &amp; Pater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num ſumus: hoc eſt, ſubſtantialiter Idem, &amp; in Perſonis Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtincti:</hi> In which few words, both the Hereſy of the <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Sabellians</hi> is ſufficiently confuted. For, as learned <hi>Athanaſius</hi> obſerveth, (who for this was happily called the World's Eye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did ſee ſo much, and pierce ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119631:23"/>far, into this unſearchable and ineffable Myſtery) we muſt neither confound the Perſons with <hi>Sabellius,</hi> nor divide the Subſtance with <hi>Arrius,</hi> for there is one Perſon of the Father, another of the Sonne, another of the Holy Ghoſt, but the God-head of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt, is all One; the Glory equal, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty co-eternal; ſuch as the Father is, ſuch is the Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore the Glory, Honour, and Worſhip, that is done to the One is done to the other, or is both due, and ought to be done, to the other. How then can it be otherwiſe, that the leaſt Homage. Honour, and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is done to <hi>Christ</hi> on this day, is accepted of God, if it be done in Faith and Obedience? Why then do you ſay, That by keeping this day, you are fearful leſt you ſhould offend God, and ſet up a day againſt Him? It may be you will object, and ſay here, as you do in your thirteenth Argument, that God is in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places much diſhonoured by the great Abuſe and Diſorders that is committed at this time. To this I briefly anſwer by the way, according to that true and well-known Rule, The Abuſe of any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119631:23"/>good thing cannot abrogate or take away the right and lawful Uſe of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why ſhould you fear, when there is no ſuch juſt cauſe at all to fear? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what <hi>Christ</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.48. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall receive me, receiveth Him that ſent me;</hi> and in the ſame place, and upon the very ſame occaſion, when <hi>John</hi> told Him ſaying, <hi>Maſter, we ſaw one caſting out Devils in thy name, and we forbade him, becauſe he followeth not with us;</hi> But Jeſus ſaid, <hi>For bid him not, for there is no man which ſhall do a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in my Name, that can lightly speak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of Me; for he that is not againſt us is for us.</hi> And I am verily perſwaded in my Soul and Conſcience, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is truly, really, and ſincerely, addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and devoted to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> neither can, nor will, ſpeak a word amiſs againſt the due Feſtivity and Solemnity of this day; thus (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. One man eſteemeth one day above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, another eſteemeth every day alike; Let every man be perſwaded in his own mind, he that regardeth a day regardeth it to the Lord; and I am perſwaded, if any man regard this day as he ought to do, the Lord will both regard &amp; reward him for ſo doing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="answer">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119631:24"/>
               <head>Anſwer to the fifth Argument.</head>
               <p>The fifth Argument is this; <hi>It is the Devil's policy to imitate God, and when he will be holy, he will be holier then God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sir, This Argument is as ſtrange ſtuff as ever I have either ſeen, felt, heard, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; for although the antecedent part cannot be much misliked, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken <hi>pro conceſſo, &amp; confeſſo,</hi> for a thing granted and confeſſed to be true, that it is the Devils policy to imitate God (for in many things he is God's Ape, as ſome Divines compare him), ſeeking to counterfeit and reſemble him as an Ape doth a Man, in ſuch ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and tricks which he uſeth; and where God will have his Church he will have his Chappel, and he will have his Exorciſms, and Charms and Spells inſtead of God's-ſpell, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; but your Sequel or Subſequent, is a meer new fangled Parodox, and a Propoſition, or rather a Suppoſition, which is not onely abſurd, but ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; not onely erroneous, but alſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119631:24"/>blaſphemous; and may be ranked and reckoned amongſt thoſe evil-ſurmiſings, and perverſe diſputings which are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. and are utterly condemned by him: but let us examine what you ſay in the latter part, <hi>viz. That when the Devil will be holy, he will be holier then God;</hi> And is that poſſible? But you inſtance for an example thus; When he ſeeth God will have a Sabbath to be kept, then will he ſet up a Day, and he will have a <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day to be kept; <hi>ô monstrum, horrendum,</hi> what a horrible, terrible ſecret is this! Is <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophers? is Sathan a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints of God? Is it poſſible? or, it is probable? or, is it any way likely to be true? That he that was (even like the great <hi>Turk</hi>) an Enemy to Chriſt and all Chriſtendom, ſhould ſo far be a friend and favourer of Chriſt, as to be a prime and forward Erector, Abettor, and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter up of a Day for the celebrating and ſetting forth of his Praiſe and Honour: Alas! if this be ſo, in what a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pittiful caſe are we, and how have we and our forefathers been led hoodwinckt (as it were) and blindfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all this while, and have been taken
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119631:25"/>in the ſnare of the Devil, and be Captive by him at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. We have ſure ſerved a very ill Saint all this while, if, like the People of <hi>Callicut,</hi> we have worſhipped the Devil in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that Day which you affirm he hath ſet up; but I ſay it is not ſo, Good Sir, for <hi>toto erras coelo,</hi> you are fouly and groſly deceived in this point. Shall you, or any man alive make me believe that ever the Devil had any deſire or inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this way, to propagate or promote the Cauſe of Chriſt, or of his Goſpel; who was ever an Adverſary, <hi>bonis incoeptis in germine,</hi> and whoſe continual and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie practiſe is, <hi>ſuffocare Dei filios, dum parvuli ſunt,</hi> to ſmother and murder the Children of God while they are little ones. Was it not he who ſtirred up <hi>Pharoah</hi> at the firſt, and moved him to command and charge the Midwives to drown the male-children of the Hebrew Women ſo ſoon as they were born, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.22? And was it not this Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or Factor, or rather that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, called the Devil and Sathan, who went about the ſame deſigne at Chriſt's birth? did not he inſtigate <hi>Herod</hi> to ſend his Men of Warr, and to kill all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119631:25"/>the young Children of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> from two years Old and under, intending thereby to murder Chriſt in Infancy and Childhood: wherefore, as devout <hi>Bernard</hi> cryeth out in the like Caſe, ſo may we; <hi>ô malitia Herediana naſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem perſequi Chriſtum, &amp; naſcentem perſequi religionem; O Herodian malice,</hi> to perſecute Chriſt and his Religion in their minority, to deſtroy the Sprigg, leſt it become a Tree, and break the Egg, leſt it prove a Dove, O diveliſh malice indeed! for (as Expoſitors upon the place aptly obſerve, and apply it thus) <hi>Herod</hi> repreſents the Devil,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.4</note> who ſtands before the Woman in the Wilderneſſe great with Child, ready to devour her Babe;
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> He knew that the ſeed which ſhould break his head, was to be born of the Jews, and therefore cauſed <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> to murder all the Hebrew Males, <hi>Exod,</hi> 1. <hi>And ſtirred up</hi> Haman <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the whole Nation of the Jews,</hi> Eſther 3. <hi>And</hi> Athalia <hi>to kill all the ſons of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. 2 King. 12. <hi>And ſo ſoon as the noiſe was of Chriſt's Birth,</hi> Herod <hi>was troubled, and all</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with him,</hi> Math. 2. And he ſent incontinent to cut the throats of all the Children
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119631:26"/>in <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> yea, more then this (if if you will believe <hi>Joſephus,</hi> who is a credible Author, and a ſufficient Repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that which was true, being <hi>testis oculatus,</hi> an eye-witneſs of many things which he wrote of, and ſaw them acted and done before his eyes) this malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crafty Fox <hi>Herod</hi> (as he tells us <hi>lib. antiquit.</hi> 10.) put to death almoſt all the Nobility of <hi>Juda,</hi> and burned the Genealogies of their Kings and Princes, commanding a Pedigree to be drawn out for himſelf, as deſcending from the Kings of <hi>Juda.</hi> This was a right Matchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avilian policy, and a deep ſleight and ſtratagem of Sathan, to extirpate and eradicate the name of Chriſt, and the name of Chriſtians for being a People from under Heaven: How then ſhall we think, or believe it, that he hath any will or deſire to ſet up a Day for Chriſt, or to have him worſhipped or adored, who ſet upon Chriſt in the Wilderneſſe, and tempted Him, by proffering the whole World, and all the Kingdomes and Glory of it to Him, if he would but ſall down and worſhip Him: So that you plainly ſee, he had rather be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped himſelf, then to have Chriſt to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119631:26"/>be worſhiped; All his chief aim is to have the Power and Kingdom of Chriſt to be leſſened and diminiſhed, and his own Kingdome to be enlarged and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced. But what did our Saviour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer? or how did he reſiſt his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Why, ſurely he defied him, and put him from him, with an <hi>Apage Satana,</hi> Avoid Sathan, <hi>or get thee hence Sathan; For it is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and Him onely ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> Math. 4.10. As if he had ſaid, If thou wilt not worſhip and ſerve him in Faith and Love, thou ſhalt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to worſhip him in fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: and for this end is he reſerved in everlaſting Chains under darkneſs, unto the Judgment of the great day, ſaith St. <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle, at the 8. <hi>ver.</hi> As for Chriſt we know that <hi>all Power is given unto Him, both in Heaven and Earth,</hi> Math. 28. And this was it that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <hi>Gabriel</hi> intimated to the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> when he ſaluted her with that firſt happy and ever-joyful news of bringing forth a Son; He ſhall be great (ſaith he) and ſhall be called the Son of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and the Lord ſhall give unto him the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119631:27"/>ſhall Raign over the Houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> for ever, and of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end: <hi>Semper regnabit quem mater virge generabit,</hi> It was the anſwer which <hi>Octavius</hi> the Emperour received from the Oracle, concerning his Succeſſor. And <hi>David</hi> himſelf foretold as much of him; ſaying, Pſal. 145.13. <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is an everlaſting Kingdome, and thy Dominion endureth throughout all Ages.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the ſixth Argument.</head>
               <p>The ſixth Argument is this, <hi>If I ſhould celebrate this Day, I am fearful lest I ſhould be condemned for accuſing God for want of wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, As our Saviour ſaith, <hi>This is the condemnation</hi> (or this is the cauſe of mens condemnation as <hi>Beza</hi> interprets the place), <hi>that light is come into the World, and men loved darkneſſe rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evil. For in Him was life, and the life was the light of men, and the light ſhined in darkneſs, and the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe comprehended it not,</hi> John 1.4, 5. <hi>(i.e.)</hi> The darkneſs that was in the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119631:27"/>thoughts and cogitations, and the Vail of blindneſſe that was upon the hearts of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.15</note> when <hi>Moſes</hi> was read unto them, cauſed them that they could neither apprehend nor compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend this light; And therefore they are both cenſured and condemned by the Apoſtle for want of wiſdome, and for want of a diſcerning Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23, 24. For after that, in the wiſdome of God, the World by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knew not God; it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching [or by that preaching which the wiſe men of the World counted fooliſhneſſe] to ſave them that believe: for the <hi>Jews</hi> require a ſigne, and the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſeek after wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but we preach Chriſt Crucified, unto the <hi>Jews</hi> a ſtumbling block, and unto the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſſe: but unto them which are called, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks;</hi> Chriſt the Power of God, and the wiſdom of God: becauſe the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is wiſer then Men, and the weakneſs of God ſtronger then Men. And therefore I wire you not, for being careful and chary of accuſing God for want of wiſdom, as they did: and yet whereas you ſay further, you are fearfull
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119631:28"/>leſt you ſhould make your ſelf wiſer then God, as though He knew not what ſhould be done as well as you, and ſo derogate from the wiſdome of God, and herein ſo far as I conceive your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you ſeem a little to derogate from the wiſdome of God, thinking your ſelf not bound to keep this Day, becauſe God in his wiſdome hath not directly revealed, or particularly nominated and ſet down in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> and <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> or in the Regiſter or Calender of his Word, what day his Son Chriſt was born, and there injoyned and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it to be obſerved and kept, which, albeit he hath not done it imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from his own mouth: yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately or miniſterially hath he done it by that heavenly Trumpeter of his, the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who particularly did Preach, promulgate, expreſs and declare it openly in the Fields to thoſe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> for this thing was not done in ſecret, nor in a corner. Now I proceed to the ſeventh Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="answer">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119631:28"/>
               <head>Anſwer to the ſeventh Argument.</head>
               <p>The words of the ſeventh Argument are theſe; <hi>if I ſhould obſerve this day, I am fearful lest I ſhould be the more inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable for my Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, This quirk or tranſcendent ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity (as I may ſo call it) is but <hi>petitio principii,</hi> and no better than <hi>idem per i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> (i. e.) no more then you have ſaid in ſome of the former: yet, in this caſe I will not ſay to you as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 14.21.</note> when he adventuring preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to walk upon the Water, was afraid, and his heart deceiving him, or rather his Faith fayling him, he began to ſink; immediately whereupon, Jeſus ſtretched forth his hand and caught him, and ſaid unto him, <hi>O thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</hi> So, wherefore do you ſear, leſt, if you ſhould keep this Day, (I mean) the Day of Chriſt's Nativity, that then you ſhould be the more inexcuſable for your fins? What, do you conceit that your carefull and conſcionable obſerving of this time ſhall add to the weight of your ſins? or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119631:29"/>increaſe the meaſure and number of your impieties? What a ſtrange and wonderful, anxious and penſive ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and prejudicate or prepoſterous miſdeeming is this? Wherefore as our Saviour cheared and comforted his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples againſt the Perſecutions and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations which they feared would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them after his departure from them, <hi>John</hi> 14.1. So let me, with your leave, a little rectifie, and direct you in this point; <hi>Let not your heart be troubled, ye believe in God, believe alſo in me:</hi> and I verily believe it, and am ſtrongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that in doing this thing which, you ſay, you are fearful to do, leſt you ſhould be the more inexcuſable for your ſins; you ſhall be ſo far from being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and condemned for it, that it ſhall rather be a means to excuſe you, and a help to hide and cover your ſins at the day of Judgment: and all the harm I wiſh unto you or my ſelf, or to any of the deareſt and neareſt Friends that <hi>I</hi> have in his World, is, that we had no greater Crime or Offence then this to anſwer for, at the great and terrible Day of our general and common appearance. For then ſhould we be acquitted and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119631:29"/>diſmiſſed with that ſentence of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I mean with that joyful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and ſoul-reviving ſentence of <hi>Venite Benedicti,</hi> Come ye bleſſed: And for your further ſatisfaction herein, and better confirmation of that which I have affirmed and averred: Let me give you a hint and inſtance of it, in that one and remarkable example of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> who though ſhe were a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Malefactor, and a great and grievous Sinner,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.</note> as the Hiſtory Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical effigiates, and ſets her forth unto us: yet, hearing that Jeſus ſate down to meat in a Phariſee's houſe, ſhe preſn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and made bold to go into the houſe; and bringing an Alablaſter-Box of Oyntment, ſhe ſtood at his feet behind him weeping, and began to waſh his feet with tears; and did wipe them with the hairs of her head, and kiſſed his feet, and anointed them with the Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now when the Phariſee which had bidden him, ſaw it, he ſpake within himſelf being diſcontented; ſaying, <hi>This man if he were a Prophet, would have known who, and what manner of Woman this is that toucheth him: for ſhe is a Sinner:</hi> And Jeſus anſwering, ſaid
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119631:30"/>unto him, <hi>Simon,</hi> I have ſomewhat to ſay unto thee; and he ſaith, Maſter ſay on: <hi>There was a certain Creditor who had two Debtors, the one owed five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pence, and the other fifty; and when they had nothing to pay, He freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave them hoth: tell me therefore, which of them will love him moſt? Simon</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid, <hi>I ſuppoſe that he to whom he forgave most,</hi> and he ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou haſt rightly judged:</hi> And he turned unto the Woman, and ſaid unto <hi>Simon, Seeſt thou this Woman? I entred into thy Houſe, Thou gavest me no water for my Feet, but ſhe hath waſhed my Feet with tears, and wiped them with the hairs of her head; Thou gaveſt me no kiſſe, but this Woman ſince the time I came in, hath not ceaſed to kiſſe my Feet: My Feet with Oyl thou didſt not anoint, but this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath anointed my Feet with Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Wherefore, I ſay unto thee, <hi>Her ſins which are many, are forgiven; for ſhe loved much: but to whom little is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the ſame loveth little:</hi> Where the Argument is not (as learned <hi>Fulk</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth, and as the whole diſcourſe of the Text makes it manifeſt) from the Cauſe to the Effect, but from the Effect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119631:30"/>to the Cauſe, Many ſins are forgiven her, therefore ſhe hath loved much; (for our Saviour had caſt ſeven Devils out of her), therefore ſhe had good cauſe to love him much, for to whom little is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he loveth little, wherefore our Saviour preferrs and extolleth her kindneſſe both above, and before the entertainment of the Phariſees Houſe. So that, if we in like manner do ſhew our love to Chriſt freely and chearfully, in celebrating the memoriall of his Birth, as ſhe did in token of his Burial, we ſhall not onely be excuſed but accepted as ſhe was; for as St. <hi>Mark</hi> relates the ſame ſtory more briefly, <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 4. When there were ſome that murmured at it, and had indignation within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſaying, <hi>Why was this waſte of the Oyntment made, for it might have been ſold for more then three hundred pence, and have bin given to the poor?</hi> But Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid by way of Apology for her, <hi>Let her alone, Why trouble you her? She hath wrought a good work on me: for you have the poor with you alwayes; and whenſoever ye will, you may do them good, but me you have not alwayes: She hath done what ſhe could, ſhe is come aforehand to anoint my Body to the Burying. Verily
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119631:31"/>I ſay unto you, Whereſoever the Goſpel ſhall be preached thorow out the whole World, this alſo that ſhe hath done, ſhall be ſpoken for a memoriall of her,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>for a memoriall of her love, of that good work that ſhe hath bestowed upon me.</hi> Wherefore as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> anſwers ſome who made a queſtion, How it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Virgin ſhould bring forth a Child, <hi>Fides adſit &amp; nulla quaeſtio remanebit;</hi> So I ſay to you, <hi>Si amor adſit timor, iſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movebit,</hi> if you love Chriſt in ſincerity, as you ought to do, then this fear will ſoon remove, and expell ſuch timorous Niceties, and frivolous Scrupuloſities out of your mind: for what ſaith the Apoſtle St. <hi>John, There is no fear in love, but perfect love caſteth out fear; becauſe fear hath torment, or fear hath painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 1 John 4.18. And let this ſuffice for the anſwering of the ſeventh Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the eighth Argument.</head>
               <p>The words of the eighth Argument are theſe, <hi>It ſeems to me a vain and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thing:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119631:31"/>
               <p>To this Argument I anſwer firſt in the words of the Roman Oratour, <hi>Quaedam videntur &amp; non ſunt,</hi> ſome things ſeem to be that which they are not; for accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Opinion of the Philoſopher, <hi>Quando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſenſus fallitur circa proprium Objectum,</hi> ſometimes the ſenſe is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved about its proper Object; as when a Man ſeeth a Buſh a far off he takes it to be a Man, which when he cometh neer it, he finds it to be no ſuch matter: even as the Man in the Goſpel, having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a little glimpſe and glimmering of his ſight, thought he ſaw men walk like Trees, (<hi>i.e.</hi>) he took them to be as bigg as Trees, becauſe the Organ of his Eye, being not ſufficiently cleanſed, he could not otherwiſe diſcern them, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.24. But it ſeems to you to be a vain and needleſs thing. What? Is it a vain and needleſs thing to ſerve God? It ſeems there were ſome who both thought and ſpake ſo in, <hi>Malachi</hi>'s time:
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.13, 14.</note> but their groſs error and their madneſs was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Prophet; even as St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us that <hi>Balaam</hi> was rebuked for his Iniquity: the dumb <hi>Aſſe,</hi> ſpeaking with Man's veice, forbade the madneſs of that falſe Propher, becauſe he loved the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119631:32"/>of Unrighteouſneſs, &amp; went beyond his permiſſion, being blinded with the hope of Bribes and Rewards of Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.16.</note> and, Is it (think you) a vain thing &amp; unprofitable to ſerve the Lord? as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the Temanite ſaith, <hi>Job</hi> 4.7. <hi>Who ever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed being innocent.</hi> So, who ever waited on the Lord and went away unreward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? He that ſerveth himſelf ſerveth a Fool; He that ſerveth the Devil ſerveth his Enemy; He that ſerveth the World ſerveth his Servant; The onely true free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is, to ſerve the Lord: For <hi>Godlineſs with Contentment is great Gain</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) 1 Tim. 6.6. <hi>yea, it is profitable unto all things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>having promiſe of the life which now is, &amp; of that which is to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.8. How then can you ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify or affirm it to be a vain &amp; needleſs thing to ſpend this time in the publick Worſhip and Service of God; namely, in the duties of Piety, and exerciſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in hearing of the Word, &amp; in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up Prayers &amp; Praiſes to God, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating it, &amp; lauding his holy and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name, with Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs. ſinging and making me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody in our hearts to the Lord,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.19, 20.</note> giving thanks alwaies, for all things, unto God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119631:32"/>and the Father, in the Name of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And eſpecially, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, giving thanks for this one thing; I mean, that ineſtimable benefit and unſpeakable gift which God beſtowed upon the World at this time. And me thinks, to this end and purpoſe we may very well encourage and ſtirr up our ſelves with the words of <hi>David,</hi> and ſay as he doth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.31, 32. I will praiſe the name of God with a Song; and magnify it with thankſgiving, this alſo ſhall pleaſe the Lord better than a Bullock which hath horns and hoofs; yea this ſhall be as precious and odoriferous in his Noſtrils, and no leſs pleaſing and acceptable in his ſight than that right &amp; coſtly <hi>Spikenard</hi> which was ſpent to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint our Saviour's feet withall; although it be ſaid of that, That <hi>the whole Houſe</hi> wherein our Saviour was at that time <hi>was filled and perfumed with the odour of the Oyntment,</hi> Joh. 12.3.</p>
               <p>But the Reaſons you alledge, to prove it to be a vain and needleſs thing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this day, are in the next place to be examined and conſidered; the firſt whereof is this, as you affirm it, becauſe God hath ſet apart a Sabbath, the Lord's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119631:33"/>for this purpoſe, to meditate upon God's Love in redeeming the World, and this ſeems to be an indifferent good one; yet you know, or at the leaſt cannot but know, that the Sabbath, or the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, was at the firſt ordained, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and ſet apart, onely in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the World's Creation, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that paſſage or Concluſion of the fourth Commandment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>For in ſix daies the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is: Wherefore the Lord bleſſed the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, and hallowed it:</hi> For this Commandment is hedged in on every ſide, leſt we ſhould break out from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it; with a <hi>Caveat</hi> and ſpeciall <hi>Memorandum</hi> before it, <hi>Remember</hi> &amp;c. and with two Reaſons after; one drawn from the Equity of the Law, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken from the Law-giver's, or the Law-maker's, own Example: <hi>Six daies ſhalt thou labour;</hi> As if God ſhould ſpeak thus, If I permit thee ſix whole daies to follow thine own buſineſs, thou mayeſt well afford me one onely for my own Service; but ſix daies ſhalt thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and do all thine own work, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hallow the Seventh in doing my
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119631:33"/>work. <hi>Six daies ſhalt thou labour;</hi> whereupon, both Reverend <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that learned Gentleman B. <hi>Babington,</hi> who was once Biſhop of this Dioceſſe, a man of no mean Note, but of good Report both for Life and Learning, do obſerve, That theſe Words (<hi>Six daies ſhalt thou labour</hi> &amp;c.) are a permiſſion, or a remiſſion of God's right, who might challenge all, rather than an abſolute Commandment: For as Judicious <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> hath alſo delivered it in his Golden Chaine, for a ſound, Orthodoxal, and undeniable <hi>Theſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Catenâ au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reâ,</hi> cap. 13</note> The Church upon juſt occaſion may ſeparate ſome week daies alſo to the Service of the Lord, and reſt from Labour, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.15. <hi>Blow the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet in Zion, ſanctify a Faſt; call a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſſembly.</hi> And as daies of publick Faſting for ſome great Judgment, ſo daies of publick Rejoycing for ſome great Benefit, are not unlawfull, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding commendable, yea, neceſſary: And you cannot in Modeſty, and I hope you will not for Shame, deny this to be the Truth; for beſides the ordinary Sabbath, among the Jews, they had their Sabbaths, and their new Moons, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Feaſts; yea, Almighty God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119631:34"/>himſelf ordained, in the old Teſtament, divers and ſundry Feaſts, to put his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in mind of his great Benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them: Amongſt the reſt there were three ſolemn Feſtivals every year; namely, the Paſsover, the Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt, and the Feaſt of Tabernacles, as we read in the 16th of <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> The Paſsover was inſtituted in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the deliverance from <hi>Egypt</hi>'s bondage; Pentecoſt, in remembrance of the Law, given in Mount <hi>Sinui;</hi> The Feaſt of Tabernacles, in remembrance of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s dwelling in Tents forty years in the Wilderneſs: Now, as <hi>Hemingius</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Postil. dom.</hi> 1. <hi>poſt Epiph.</hi> inſtead of thoſe three Jewiſh Feaſts, our Chriſtian Church (which may challenge as much Liberty as the Jewiſh, if not more) hath ſubſtituted <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Incarnation; Eaſter, in honour of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Reſurrection; and Whitſuntide, in honour of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Goſpel, by ſending un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the Holy Ghoſt at that time; So that we ſay, according as <hi>St. Auſtin</hi> ſaith in his 108 <hi>Epist. cap.</hi> 1, <hi>Celebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Anniverſariâ ſolemnitate Paſcha, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Chriſtianas diêrum Feſtivitutes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119631:34"/>non obſervamus tempora, ſed quae illis ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificantur temporibiu:</hi> (i.e.) In celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Easter,</hi> and other Chriſtian Feaſts, we do not ſo much obſerve the times, as the things that are repreſented and ſignified unto us at thoſe times. If then it be granted, as it cannot be denied, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your words, that God hath ſet apart a Sabbath (which is our Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Sabbath) and is called the Lord's Day, becauſe the Lord roſe from death to life on that Day, and that on this day (in that reſpect) we are to meditate on God's Love in redeeming the World; if we muſt do this once every week in an ordinary courſe, how much more may the Church and Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, and ſet apart, one day in the year, after an extraordinary manner, to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and muſe, and think on his Love in redeeming her from the hands of all her Enemies; for ſo indeed the holy Prieſt <hi>Zacharias</hi> tells us, in his Song called <hi>Benedictus,</hi> That this was the main End of our Redemption, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74. <hi>that we being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without fear, in holineſs and righteouſneſs, all the daies of our Life:</hi> Whereupon I infer, That
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119631:35"/>if we muſt ſerve him all the daies of our life, as he may juſtly challenge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it at our hands, in regard he hath redeemed us, How much more ought we to meditate on his Love, not onely once a week, but alſo once in every year praiſe his moſt Holy Name after a more ſpeciall and ſingular manner? For at this time eſpecially and particularly, it may be ſaid of Him, as the Pſalmiſt doth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.9. <hi>He ſent Redemption unto his People; He hath commanded his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for ever, holy and reverend is His Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, in your ſecond Reaſon, you ſay That you never heard a good Argument for it: Well, be it ſo as you ſay, yet I dare ſay, that you ſay it, not ſo much out of your Ignorance, as through a miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and ſiniſter Interpretation of that which you have both heard and read concerning this thing: Wherefore for anſwering you, firſt, <hi>Hoc tibi inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſcere velimus,</hi> we do you to wit, or would have you to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That albeit the gray-headed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and Authority of our dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the uniform Diſcipline with Us eſtabliſhed,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119631:35"/>for ſome Centuries of years, making and conſtituting it an antient and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order, and generally approved Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, may be a ſufficient Plea, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and VVarrant to perſwade you, or any other rational man to conſent and conforme unto it; for what ſaith grave St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> He that will have God to be his Father, muſt acknowledge the Church of God for his Mother: and then, let every Member of this Church remember that good and wholeſome advice of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, Prov. 11.8. <hi>My Son, hear thy Fathers Instruction, and forſake not thy Mothers teaching:</hi> For St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us in his Epiſt. 118. <hi>Extremae eſt dementiae ſeu inſolentis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaniae, ea negligere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> repudiare quae tota obſervat eccleſia.</hi> It is extream folly, and inſolent madneſſe to neglect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, to obſerve thoſe things which the whole Church (whereof we are born Members) doth obſerve; yet for your better ſatisfaction herein, I have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and purpoſe to bring in a few Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which perhaps may be thought by ſome to be as good, and ſtrong, and forcible for the keeping of this Day, as any you have hi her to urged, or may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119631:36"/>hereafter deviſe and produce, againſt it.</p>
               <p>The firſt that I ſhall propound and preſent to your quaint and curious and ſupercilious cenſure, or to your Auſtere and Rigid conſideration, ſhall be the Legality and lawfulneſs of Ordering and Ordaining, and ſetting apart of ſome dayes of publick Thankſgiving, and holy rejoycing to the Lord for great Benefits, and publick Bleſſings received; which, if this day of Chriſt his Incarnation and Manifeſtation in the fleſh, might be but ſet up and celebrated amongſt the reſt as it deſerveth, I am perſwaded it would contend and ſtrive ſo for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority and Preheminence above the reſt, that it would even devour and ſwallow the reſt up, as <hi>Aarons</hi> Serpent did the Serpents of thoſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians and Praeſtigiators; or excell them, and caſt them down, as the Ark did <hi>Dagon;</hi> or as the Image of Chriſt when it was placed by the Senators at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Capitol, threw down the Image of <hi>Jupiter, Mars, Mercury,</hi> and others of their feigned heatheniſh gods, as <hi>Enſebius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> report it for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119631:36"/>truth; and the Men of this Generation would ſoon condeſcend and yield to this motion, and not deny nor gain-ſay this reaſonable propoſition, if they were not too much like thoſe blind and blinded Phariſees among the Jews, who were for the moſt part, <hi>culicem excolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; Camelum deglutientes,</hi> apt and inclined to ſtrain at a Gnat, and ſwallow a Cammel, <hi>Math.</hi> 23, 24. <hi>For if it be lawful to give God thanks for Corporal and Temporal Deliverances, How much more for our Spiritual and Eternal Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance by Chriſt, from the thraldome of ſinne and Sathan;</hi> Again, If it ſhall be thought lawful and allowable to praiſe God for the ſpilling of blood,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 6.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of Mens lives, (which yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 2.8.</note> nor the Prophet <hi>Oded</hi> would allow of;) how much more then ſhall it be lawfull and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to praiſe the Lord for the ſparing and preſerving of Mens lives, and for the ſaving of their Souls, and freeing or delivering both their Bodies and Souls from the everlaſting pains and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Death and Hell; <hi>For the Son of Man came to ſeak and ſave that which was loſt, and God ſent not his Son into the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119631:37"/>World, to condemn the World, but that the World through Him might be ſaved,</hi> Joh. 3.17.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Argument which I ſhall here ſet down for the ſolemnity of this Day, I will make bold to borrow from the words of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which, I do not onely conjecture, but preſume, were Preached and Delivered by him on the very Day; we find them recorded in his Serm. 2. &amp; 4. <hi>de tempore;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (ſaith he), all of us are bidden on this Day to a Marriage, for Chriſt came out of the Virgins Womb, as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom out of his Chamber; the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head was joyned unto the Fleſh, and the Fleſh unto the God-head, and theſe two were coupled together; and, after an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable manner, in an ineffable Marriage made one. The marriage-Chamber was the Virgins Womb, (which he abhorred not) out of which that Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Chriſt Jeſus came in the day of his Birth, as a Bridegroom out of his Chamber,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> and as a ſtrong man joyfull to run his race. For the Son of God, knowing that according to the eternall decree enacted in the Court of Heaven,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119631:37"/>our Salvation could not be perfected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Incarnate;
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> in the fulneſſe of time, came down (ſealing our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) with rejoycing of Spirit, and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, exſuiting, trium phing, and preparing himſelf to the deſired work of his mediatorſhip. Long had the Church waited and prayed for this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt in the fleſh:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.1.</note> 
                  <hi>O would God thou wouldeſt burſt the Heavens, and come down:
<note place="margin">Cant. 8.1.</note> O that then werſt as my Brother, which ſucked the breaſt of my Mother, partaking the ſame humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with me.</hi> I would find thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, here below on Earth, I would kiſſe thee, and familiarly intreat thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the reproach of the World. Then I would lead thee, and bring thee into my Mothers houſe, though now I am penned up in the Straights of <hi>Judea,</hi> I would bring thee into the Light and Knowledge of the Univerſal Church, whoſe Daughter I am; and herefore he was worthily called <hi>deſideratus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium gentium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> the deſired of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but when he came, he came merily; with nimbleneſs of Spirit, zeal of Piety, fervency of Love, as the Church eſpying him, joyfully relates it; It is the voice
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119631:38"/>of my well-beloved,
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, he cometh leaping by the Mountains, skipping by the Hills: My well-beloved is like a Roe or Hart.</hi> He came flying on the wings of the Wind, he out-leapt <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Archangel, and came to the Virgin before him, by the Teſtimony of the Angel himſelf:
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.27.</note> Hail <hi>Mary,</hi> full of grace, the Lord is with thee. Behold, <hi>Gabriel</hi> left Chriſt in Heaven, but finds him in the Womb: How ſo? <hi>Volavit &amp; praevolavit ſuper pennas vontorum,</hi> he flew, and out-flew him on the wings of the wind; he ſent his Meſſenger, but (like <hi>Ahinoaz</hi>) got before him. Will you ſee his Jumps? He lept from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the Womb, from the Womb to the Manger, from the Manger to the Croſſe, from the Croſſe to the Grave, from the Grave to Heaven again: from whence we look for, and expect his ſecond coming. <hi>David</hi> ſang of this his alacrity;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>The King is glad of thy ſtrength (O Lord) and exceeding joyfull of thy Salvation, Quia verbum caro factum est, &amp; habitavit in nobis;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſaith <hi>Augustine</hi> on thoſe words), <hi>The Word was made fleſh, and dwelt in us,</hi> the Day of Chriſt's Nativity was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119631:38"/>his Day of Feſtivity, his Birth Day was his Mirth Day, for then his Mother Crowned him with the Crown of his Incarnation; which was the Day of his Eſpouſals, or the Day of the joy and gladneſs of his heart, as it is ſo called, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.10. This is a great Myſtery (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>), but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and the Church; <hi>&amp;, ſine dubio, magnum est pietatis myſterium;</hi> And without controverſy great is the Myſtery of godlineſs; How God was manifeſted in the Fleſh, juſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the VVorld,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> and received up in Glory; and He being thus aſcended and received up into Glory; for the Heaven muſt receive Him (in regard of his bodily preſence) untill the times of reſtitution of all things, ſaith <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 3.21. And thus, leaving his Spouſe the Church as a VViddow, as He hath enjoyned and Commanded her in the Goſpel to think upon his Love, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to remember him and his Death, eſpecially as often as ſhe receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bleſſed Sacraments of his Body and Blood: So ſhe for her part thinks it meet not onely to Commemorate his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119631:39"/>Death, but ſometimes, alſo eſpecially once a year to Congratulate and Solace her ſelf in remembrance of his Birth; That happy and joyful Marriage day which was once Solemnized betwixt her and that great King of Glorie's Son, who now ſitteth at the right hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven: even as I have alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it to be the faſhion and condition of many good and honeſt Couples whilſt they live on Earth together, to keep a ſolemn remembrance every year of their Wedding day, even untill their Dying day: So ſhould every good Chriſtian and faithful Soul keep a due and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual remembrance of her Loving Lord, and gracious Head and Husband, Chriſt Jeſus. As it is reported of that famous <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> That to ſhew her love to her dead Husband <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> ſhe took the aſhes of his Urne or Pitcher, and mingled them with her Drink, and ſo intombed his dead Carkaſſe within her living Body: And it is ſaid of bleſſed <hi>Ignatius</hi> after his Martyrdome, that theſe words were found written upon his heart (ſo it were to be wiſhed that they were alſo ingraven and imprinted in Ours) <hi>Amor mens crucifixus,</hi> my
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119631:39"/>Love Chriſt Jeſus was crucified for me. But perhaps here you, will object, and ſay, that this is <hi>Symbolica Theologiae,</hi> and that it is not <hi>Argumentativa,</hi> (i. e.) that it is an Argument Rhetorical rather than Dialectical. What ſay you then to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia miraculis confirmata:</hi> which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the third place I ſhall alleadge; namely, the ſtrange accidents, and wonderful effects that happened at the Birth of Chriſt, or rather thoſe rare and ſingular miracles that were acted and done near about the time of his Nativity: For a little before, this was it that made a young Babe while he was yet in the Womb of his Mother to Spring and Sprout, and leap therein for joy; yea,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.44.</note> this was it that made an old man that was dumb before, to ſpeak, and to praiſe the Lord with a ſong; and ſay,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.6, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. And this was it that moved another old man, after he had ſeen the Lord Chriſt to hold him in his arms, and deſire life no longer. He was ſo much raviſhed and overjoyed with the ſight of his Saviour, that he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chanted out <hi>Cantionem Cygneam,</hi> that ſwanne-like ſong, <hi>Lord, now it is enough,</hi> and I am abundantly ſatisfied
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119631:40"/>becauſe thou haſt fulfilled my deſire, in performing thy promiſe to me, that I ſhould not ſee Death before I had ſeen thy Son.</p>
               <p>To theſe we may add the apparition of that glorious Starr which ſhewed it ſelf unto the Wiſe men of the Eaſt, about the time of his Nativity: which was not an ordinary Starr, but extraordinary and miraculouſly created at this time, for this very end and purpoſe, not onely to ſignifie, but to dignifie and ſet forth the Birth of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> for ſaid they, <hi>We have ſeen his Starr in the East,</hi> that is, the Starr which he hath newly made, to teſtifie unto the World, that he is born. It differed from other Starrs in Place and Motion, in Luſtre and Brightneſſe. <hi>Haec ſtella quae ſolis rotam vincit decore ac lumine,</hi> ſaith <hi>Prudentius</hi> of this Starr; it hath another way then the way of the Starrs from the Eaſt to the South, from <hi>Perſia</hi> to <hi>Palestina,</hi> it appeared not when other Stars appeared; It ſhined in the day, Other in the Night; it did appear &amp; was hid, it was hid and did appear. It ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf before they entred <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and hid it ſelf while they were there: but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119631:40"/>ſo ſoon as they left <hi>Herod</hi> and the City, it did ſhew it ſelf; and went right for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in a ſtraight courſe towards <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> no otherwiſe then the Cloud and Pillar of fire went before the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their departure, and going out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Canaan:</hi> It kept not the ordinary courſe of the Starrs, nor any proper way, for it went that way which the wiſe men would go, and when they would ſtand ſtill, then that ſtood ſtill; yea, it did not keep aloft like other Starrs, but it deſcended to ſhew the <hi>Meſſiah:</hi> the <hi>Meſſah</hi> ſo poor, ſo baſe and contemptible. Whereupon it is that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> calleth it, <hi>magnifica lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua caeli,</hi> the ſtately congue of heaven, appointed by God, as it were, to reveal and preach unto the wiſe men that Chriſt was that Starr of <hi>Jacob,</hi> propheſied of by <hi>Balaam, Numb.</hi> 24.17. that he was <hi>Stella illa ſplendida &amp; matutina,</hi> that bright Morning Starr, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.16. and that he was <hi>Oriens ab alto,</hi> that day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring from high, that came to viſit us, and to give light to them that ſit in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death, to guide our feet in the way of Peace, as that holy Prieſt <hi>Zacharias</hi> telleth us
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119631:41"/>comfortably in his ſong, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.75. Wherefore, as the Roman Orator ſpeaks, ſo will I here ſay, <hi>Nihil horum era vultus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> movernunt?</hi> and as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Poet elegantly, <hi>Quid ſatis est, ſi Roma parum:</hi> ſo will I be bold here to ſpeak it, <hi>Quid ſatis erit illi, cui non ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient iſta?</hi> If theſe things will not ſerve to convince you, I know not what will?
<note place="margin">Mark. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> For, if neither the VVord, nor Miracles, nor the VVord confirmed by Miracles, will prevail and work upon us to make us believe; then I ſay, as it is in the 16 of <hi>Luke</hi> at the laſt <hi>verſe, If they hear not</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, neither will they be perſwaded, though one roſe from the dead:</hi> Yet, willingly would I add here one ſtrange thing more or two, (which are no more ſtrange then true) as a Corollary and Appendix to the former; which though they were not Synchroniſms, or things Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraneous with the Birth of Chriſt, yet the People of our Nation, and our own Countrymen can witneſſe them to be true, as I relate them; The firſt is the Thorne at <hi>Glastenbury</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> which was commonly called <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph's</hi> Thorne: which for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119631:41"/>years together, even (as it is to be thought) ſince the firſt arriving of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> there, which was within five years after the Death and Reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus, (as that antient Hiſtorian of our Nation, the Golden-mouthed <hi>Gildas</hi> reporteth) this Thorne conſtantly budded and ſhewed forth its green leaves, fair, freſh and flouriſhing on this Day every year, to the great admiration of all Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that came of purpoſe to behold it; and this was no other then a Miracle, and may ſerve for our confirmation in the faith of Him, who, for our ſakes was contented to wear (<hi>Coronam Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam</hi>) a Crown of Thornes: Or it may well be ſuppoſed, that ir flouriſhed on this Day, to teſtifie the truth of his Nativity, and to ſignifie the flouriſhing Eſtate of the Goſpel by Him, which ſhall proſper and flouriſh, manger the head and hatred of all Gain-ſayers. And although this Thorne be now, as they ſay, cut down by ſome ſpightful and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Zoilus;</hi> yet, thoſe ſufficient men of our parts, who, with their eyes have ſeen it, and beheld it, will ſtill talk of it, and tell it to their Children, not for an
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119631:42"/>old Wives Fable, but for truth; and one Gentleman among the reſt of good rank and quality in theſe Parts (who is a man well affected and devoted to the power and purity of Religion) for that Thorn's ſake, having ſeen it, doth ſtrictly, and carefully, and conſcionably keep this Day, and is reſolved to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep it ſo long as he liveth.</p>
               <p>The other rare and ſtrange thing, are the three pitts of <hi>Durham,</hi> commonly called Hell kettles, which are adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning near unto <hi>Darlington,</hi> whoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſomewhat warm; theſe are thought to come of an Earth-quake, which happened in the year of Grace, 1179. whereof the Chronicle of <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> maketh mention, whoſe record is this; That on Chriſtmasday at <hi>Oxen-Hall,</hi> in the Territories of <hi>Darlington,</hi> within the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> the ground heaved aloft, like unto a high Tower, and ſo continued all that day, as it were unmoveable, untill the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and then fell with ſo horrible a noiſe, that it made the Neighbourhood-dwellers much afraid, and the Earth ſwallowed it up, and made in the ſame place three deep pits, which are there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119631:42"/>to be ſeen for a Teſtimony unto this Day. Here then we may apply that of the Pſalmiſt, and ſay, <hi>Tremble thou Earth at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>which tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the hard Rock into a ſtanding Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the flint ſtone into a ſpringing Well,</hi> Pſal. 114.7, 8. But whilſt I am relling you a ſtory of a Thorne-Tree, and of deep pits of Water, you bring me into another difficult and thorny queſtion, and plunge me, as it were, in a deep pit of <hi>non plus,</hi> or <hi>nil ultra;</hi> and into ſuch a quick and and quagmire of troubleſome meditation, that I ſhall hardly get out of it; the Quaery is this ninth following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the ninth Argument.</head>
               <p>The ninth Argument is this; <hi>It is an impoſſibility to keep it, and God never made an impoſſibility a Duty: and, that no man in the World knoweth certainly what day Chriſt was born on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, although I firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſſe, according to that Adage, <hi>Davus ſum ego, non Oedipus:</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119631:43"/>for it is true which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Praeſtat probâ ignoratione detineri quàm falſa opinione mancipari.</hi> It is eaſier to plow in the plain, then in the ground new-ſtocked; better to write on a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per free from writing, than on that which is full of lines; and more eaſie to reach the ſimple, then him that is opinionated of his own knowledge: Better it is for a man, and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable to confeſs a little ignorance, then to boaſt of too much knowledge; wherefore, as <hi>Beza</hi> on that place in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. <hi>For this Cauſe ought the Woman to have power on her head,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Angels gives no other note but this, <hi>Quid hoc ſit, nondum mihi liquet,</hi> wherein he confeſſeth, he did not underſtand, as yet, what the Apoſtle meant by theſe words: So if we ſhould here yield and acknowledge that we do not certainly know what day Chriſt was born on:
<note place="margin">Vaux.</note> yet, As a late Starr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazing Speculator takes upon him in his Almanack, to define the year of Chriſt his coming to Judgment, but dare not preciſely ſet down the day and hour of his coming; So perhaps we ſhall here endeavour, <hi>pro Noſſe &amp; Poſſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119631:43"/>to calculate and diſcover unto you the year when our Saviour Chriſt was born, if not the day. And for this I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr you to the Rhemiſts Marginal note on the ſecond of <hi>Luke,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports unto us that in the year from the Creation of the World 3199, from <hi>Noah</hi>'s flood 2957, from the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of <hi>Abraham</hi> 2015, from <hi>Moſes</hi> and the coming forth of the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> 1510, from <hi>David</hi> anointed King 1032, from the firſt <hi>Olympias</hi> 800, from the building of <hi>Rome</hi> 752, <hi>Hebdomada</hi> 63, according to the prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi> (<hi>c.</hi> 9.) that is in the year 440, or thereabout; in the ſixth age of the World, when there was univerſal Peace in all the World: the eternal God, and ſon of the eternal Father, meaning to Conſecrate and Sanctifie the World with his moſt bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed coming, being conceived of the Holy Ghoſt nine Months after his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God is born in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Juda,</hi> in the year of <hi>Caeſar Augustus</hi> 42 (<hi>Uſuard</hi> in the Martyrol)
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>And then why ſhould not the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> Decem. <hi>be as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and kept, as the</hi> 5 <hi>of</hi> Nov.</note> 
                  <hi>December</hi> 25 according to the common ancient ſupputation. But it may be, you will object againſt this, &amp;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119631:44"/>becauſe it comes from the Rhemiſts, you will miſlike it, and diſdain it; yet nevertheleſs (I ſay) becauſe it is not thwarted nor contradicted by <hi>Calvin,</hi> nor <hi>Beza,</hi> nor <hi>Fulke,</hi> nor any other of our late Proteſtant Writers; I ſee no juſt Cauſe or Reaſon why we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it, but rather receive it, <hi>Fide hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricâ,</hi> and believe it for truth, as it is faithfully and exactly related by them for a ſufficient Author, and ancient Chronologer, or Reporter of that which was nothing elſe but a true ſtory, and cannot be denyed or diſproved; yet, put the Caſe here that we neither do, nor cannot certainly know the Day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt was born, therefore ſhall it be thought a thing impoſſible to keep it? Then by the ſame Rule and Reaſon, you may as well ſay, It is impoſſible to keep the Sabbath day:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>H. Wolphii Chronol. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 92.</note> For the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement doth not ſay, remember to keep holy the ſeventh day, next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſixth day of the Creation; or this or that ſeventh day; but indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, remember that thou keep holy a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day. And to ſpeak properly, as we take a day for the diſtinction of time, called either a day natural conſiſting of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119631:44"/>twenty four hours; or a day artificial conſiſting of twelve hours, from Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing to Sun-ſetting: and withall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Sun ſtanding ſtill at noon in <hi>Joſhua's</hi> time the ſpace of a whole day,
<note place="margin">Joſh. 10.12, 13.</note> and the ſame going back ten degrees (<hi>viz.</hi> five hours,
<note place="margin">2 K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng. 26.11.</note> almoſt half an arifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Day) in <hi>Ezekias</hi> time; the Jews themſelves could not keep this Sabbath upon that preciſe and juſt diſtinction of time, called at the firſt, The ſeventh day from the Creation; therefore in ſuch difficult and doubtful Caſes, the beſt way is to be ordered and guided, and reſolved by the Judgment and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Direction of the Church wherein we live: for ſhe is our Mother, ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. Inſtit.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> foraſmuch as there is no other entry into life, unleſs ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us in her Womb, unleſs ſhe bring us forth, unleſs ſhe feed us with her Breaſts, and keep us under her Cuſtody and Governance, untill ſuch time as being unclothed of mortal fleſh, we ſhall be like unto Angels. Again in his <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 30. He ſaith of the Church and Church-Ordinances, that in outward diſcipline and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the will of God was not to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119631:45"/>preſcribe each thing particularly what we ought to follow, becauſe he foreſaw this to hang upon the State of times, and did not think one form to be fit for all Ages) herein we muſt fly to thoſe general Rules which he hath given, that thereby all thoſe things ſhould be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which the neceſſity of the Church ſhall require to be commanded for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and comelineſs. And foraſmuch as he hath therefore taught nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, becauſe theſe things both are not neceſſary to Salvarion, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the manners of every Nation and Age, ought diverſly to be applyed to the edifying of the Church; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the profit of the Church ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, though it might be thought convenient as well to change and abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate thoſe that be uſed, as to inſtitute new: yet, I grant it indeed, and muſt needs confeſſe it, That we ought not raſhly, nor oft, nor for leight and trivial Cauſes to run to Innovation, but what may hurt or edifie, Charity ſhall beſt be judge: which if we will ſuffer to be the Governeſs, all ſhall be ſafe. And in the next Section at the latter end thereof; It is alwayes meet, ſaith he,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119631:45"/>for the publike worſhip and ſervice of God, that there be both certain dayes and appointed hours, and a place fit to receive all, if there be regard had of the preſervation of peace. For how great an occaſion of ſcandal, brawling, and contention ſhould the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe things be, if it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for every man as he liſteth to change thoſe things which belong to common State; foraſmuch as it will never come to paſs that one and the ſame thing ſhall pleaſe all Men, (it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an old and true ſaying, <hi>difficillimum eſt omnibus placere</hi>) if things be left (as it were) at randome, and in the middeſt to the choice of every Man to do what he pleaſeth, to have a Pſalm, and a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and a Revelation, and an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation by himſelf, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh with a kind of Indignation and Increpation of them that uſed it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. If any man therefore do Carp and Cavil againſt us, and herein will be more wiſe then he ought, let him ſee himſelf by what reaſon he can defend his own preciſeneſs to the Lord. As for us, That ſaying of <hi>Paul</hi> ought to ſatisfie us; <hi>If any man ſeem to be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119631:46"/>Schiſmatical and contentious, we have no ſuch uſe, we have no ſuch Custome nor the Churches of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.16. Where we may perceive that that good Man and faithful Paſtor of <hi>Geneva,</hi> though he liked not the Maſſe, yet he preached Chriſt ſincerely, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and defended his Church, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured by all means to preſerve, <hi>Tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam ejus inconſutilem,</hi> his ſeamleſſe Coat to be without brack or breach, Sect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Schiſm, Rent or Diviſion at all; but ſtill to continue pure and undefiled without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing. I will then conclude and ſhut up this paſſage with the witty Sentences of St. <hi>Auſtin, Contrarationem nemo ſobrius, contra Scripturas nemo Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, contra eccleſiam nemo pacificus ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerii.</hi> And if we will be the Children of the Church, as we profeſſe our ſelves to be, then let us hearken what the wiſe man ſaith: Ecclus. 3.1. <hi>The Children of wiſdome are the Church of the Righteous, and their exerciſe is Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Love.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="answer">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119631:46"/>
               <head>Anſwer to the tenth Argument.</head>
               <p>The words are theſe, <hi>I obſerve, God hides things on purpoſe from us, to ſee whether we will do any things on our own heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, This Argument is derived <hi>de profundis,</hi> and drawn or fetched <hi>ab abſconditis &amp; ſecretis.</hi> 'Tis true, and we cannot much deny it; For He hideth, or concealeth from us, his Decree of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and final Dereliction or Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.13</note> becauſe he will have Mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardneth; And this he doth, becauſe he would not have us like curious <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemites</hi> to pry into the Ark of his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, but rather to work out our own Salvation with fear and trembling,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks; and as the other Apoſtle teacheth and exhorteth us,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> to give all diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure. And now is this to be underſtood? why, ſurely thus, if I be not deceived; ſure to God. I need not, I cannot,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> the Foundation of God ſtands ſure enough of it ſelf, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119631:47"/>the Gifts and Calling of God are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. (<hi>i. e.</hi>) <hi>Sine mutatione stabiliter fixa ſunt,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> they are irrevocable, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, and unchangeable; but, Sure to my own Soul, I may, I muſt, by all means labour and endeavour to make and effect it, or elſe this Precept is in vain, of <hi>giving all diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure.</hi> Secondly, He hideth the hour of every particular man's death, and the day of the generall Judgment, from us, and reſerveth them in the private Cabinet of his own Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeſhip;
<note place="margin">Act. 1.17.</note> For it is not for us to know the times and the Seaſons which the Father hath reſerved in his own Power: And this he doth for this very end, as an ancient Father of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church hath told us truly and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>Ideò latet ultimus dies, ut obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur omnis dies,</hi> It is to make us careful and watchful, every day and hour, of that laſt day and hour, <hi>Omnem crede di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em,</hi> &amp;c. And doth not our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tell us as much, and forwarn us, both in the 24. and 25. <hi>Chapter</hi> of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s Goſpel, <hi>Watch therefore, for ye neither know the day nor the hour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119631:47"/>the Son of man cometh;</hi> But whereas you ſay that God hides things on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe from us, to ſee whether we will do any thing on our own heads, I perceive your meaning is, that God hath ſo hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and concealed the day of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Birth from us, to try whether we will celebrate and obſerve it, or no, as both you and others of your Fraternity have made the Compariſon, and vented and vaunted it in the Pulpit, touching the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> how God ſhould bury it Himſelf in ſome ſecret place, and keep it from the Knowledge of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> leſt they ſhould worſhip and adore it: So you would have the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of this day to be buried for ever, and quite obliterated and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, leſt we ſhould commit Idolatry to it. Now, touching the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> we know it was buried by God, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6. that no man ſhould know where his Sepulchre was: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as learned <hi>Fulk</hi> anſwereth the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> on the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> at the 9th. verſe; It is like, the Altercation and Combat that is there mentioned to be betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel and the Devil about it, was immediately before
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119631:48"/>that time, when the Devil deſired to have the Body of <hi>Moſes</hi> diſcovered, that it might be abuſed to Idolatry; as it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hath been the practiſe of Sathan to perſecute the Saints while they live, and to make Idols of their Bodies when they are dead. That ancient Father which wrote the Book <hi>De Mirabilibus Sacrae Scripturae,</hi> which goeth under the name of St. <hi>Augaſtine lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 35. writeth thus of the body of <hi>Moſes;</hi> For two Cauſes, as wiſe men ſay, No man was privy of his death, nor of his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre; Firſt, That no man ſhould ſee that face, which had ſhined through the familiarity of the Lord's Speech unto him, ſtricken down or dimmed with the heavineſs of Death. And then Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, leſt the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if they had known where his Sepulchre was, ſhould have adored it. Wherefore, as moſt men think, he carried away with him the Rod wherewith he had done Wonders, leſt it ſhould have been ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſeeing the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did afterwards adore the Serpent which he made.</p>
               <p>But there cannot be the ſame reaſon for the burying of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Birth-day, as
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119631:48"/>was for the burying of the Body of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> It is but a lame Similitude, neither can the Compariſon be aequivaleut, or any way co-incident or correſpondent; for <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a Servant, <hi>Christ</hi> a Son; and the Servant abideth not in the Houſe for ever, but the Son abideth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Type and Shadow, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Body and Subſtance; the Shadow vaniſheth, but the Body and Subſtance remaineth. Beſides this, the one was but a Man, the other God, even God and Man; and ſhall that be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Idolatry and Superſtition, which is a holy Worſhip, and devout Service performed to the true God? So that <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt yield, ſubſcribe, and give way to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> when he is preſent, the Law muſt depart out of the Conſcience,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.20.</note> and leave the Bed which is ſo ſtrait, that it cannot hold two, to <hi>Christ</hi> alone: For the Law came by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath put an end to the Law, and ſo Grace and Truth came by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1.16.</note> (<hi>i. e.</hi>) Joy, and Liberty, and Freedom, and Juſtification, and Redemption; for if the Son once ſhall make us free, we ſhall be free indeed. For there is a great <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> even a great deal of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119631:49"/>diſtance and difference, betwixt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Law and the Goſpel; the one being the miniſtration of Death &amp; Condemnation, and the other the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Righteouſneſſe and Life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. And therefore I ſay, to conclude this Point, that this day is not ſo hidden and obſcured from us, but that the very dawning and breaking thereof is diſcovered and deſcryed: For, did not the heavenly Herald proclaim it in the fields of <hi>Bethlehem?</hi> and did not the Shepherds find it to be true, that very day, according as the Angel had told them? and ſhall we think that there were no Regiſters nor Records of it in that City wherein he was born? and did not that Starr in the Eaſt, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying this Day-Star from on high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to viſit us; did it not directly point the Wiſe-men to the place of his Birth? Yea, And <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf told the Jews of this his day,
<note place="margin">Job, 8.56.</note> ſaying, Your Father <hi>Abraham</hi> rejoyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it and rejoyced: <hi>Hic Dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini uil aliud ſignificat quàm Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Christi in carne,</hi> This day of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Beza,</hi> on that place in <hi>John</hi>) ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth nothing elſe but his firſt coming
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119631:49"/>in the Fleſh, which many Prophets and Kings deſired to have ſeen as well as <hi>Abraham;</hi> for the <hi>Meſſias</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The deſire of all Nations,</hi> Hag. 2.8. of whom the Prophets enquired, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when or what time the Spirit, which was in them, ſhould declare the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings which ſhould come to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Glory that ſhould follow, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. When <hi>Balaam</hi> had prophecyed of <hi>Christ, There ſhall come a Star out of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>and a Scepter ſhall riſe out of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.17. he brake forth into this Paſſion; <hi>Alaſs! Who ſhall live when God doth this?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Happy men are they, who ſhall ſee that glorious Star, and Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, coming out of his Chamber as a Bride-groom; giving light to ſuch as ſit in darkneſs, and in the Shadow of Death: Oh that thou wouldeſt break the Heavens and come down, ſaid the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.1. Good old <hi>Simeon</hi> looked long for this day, and with an earneſt deſire waited for the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> So did alſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathaea,</hi> that honourable Counſellor &amp; great Friend and Well-wiſher to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for he alſo himſelf was one of them who
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119631:50"/>waited for the Kingdom of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.51. So did that ancient and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> of whom it is reported that he wiſhed he might have ſeen three things eſpecially, <hi>Rome</hi> in her Glory, <hi>Paul</hi> in the Pulpit, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Fleſh. If the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> reputed the Servants of <hi>Solomon</hi> happy, for that, attending about his Throne,
<note place="margin">1 King. 10.8. 1 King. 4.33.</note> they heard his Wiſdom dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of Prees, from the Cedar that is in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> even unto the Hyſſop that ſpringeth out of the Wall: How bleſſed and happy then may we think were the Diſciples of <hi>Christ,</hi> in hearing a greater than <hi>Solomon, Math.</hi> 12.4. and in ſeeing him who was fairer than the Sons of Men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.3. and in whom alſo are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the eleventh Argument.</head>
               <p>In the Eleventh Objection you ſay, <hi>It hath not been the Practiſe of Chriſtian Churches to obſerve the Birth-day of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119631:50"/>
               <p>To this I ſay, you deſerve a ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and a ſerious and ſevere repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. For it is a meer falſhood, and a groſſe and manifeſt untruth; and I wonder that a man of your account, Countenance and gravity, ſhould ſuffer ſuch an unjuſtifiable thing, to fall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from your tongue or pen; for I ſay, <hi>contrarium hujus argumenti est ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;, credat Judaus Apella, non ego,</hi> believe it who will, for I cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be perſwaded, but you ſpeak herein that which is contrary to truth: for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it is well known among the Learned, eſpecially by thoſe who are converſant in the large Volumes, and accurate writings of the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; It hath been the annuall and conſtant Practice of the Primitive Church to obſerve it; eſpecially in the time,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. 118. Epiſt. cap. 7.</note> and ſince the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, who gave peace to the Church and commanded this Feſtivall time among divers others to be obſerved. Witneſſe <hi>Auguſt. con. Aimant.</hi> c. 16.118. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> and in divers of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>de Tempore,</hi> eſpecially in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and fourth Sermon <hi>de Tempore.</hi> Witneſſe <hi>Fulgentius de dup. Nat. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119631:51"/>witneſſe <hi>Ambroſe de Incarnat. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> witneſſe <hi>Bernard</hi> in his firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in <hi>Nat. Domini.</hi> for that ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Religions man, that witty and Godly Father of the Primitive Church, preaching on this day, in that his firſt Sermon, and towards the latter end of it, uttered theſe words, and ſaid, <hi>Brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas temporis cogit me contrahere &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arctare Sermonem meum;</hi> the ſhortneſs of the time conſtraineth me to ſhorten my Sermon, at this time; <hi>&amp; ne cui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strûm ſit mirum, ſi brevis eſſe laboro, Let none</hi> (quoth he) <hi>wonder if my words be ſhort, ſeeing on this day, God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath abbreviated his own Word:</hi> For whereas it was ſo long and ſo large, that it filled Heaven and Earth (<hi>Jer.</hi> 23.24.) it was on this day ſo ſhort, that it was laid in a Manger: I wiſh here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly, with the ſame devour <hi>Bernard</hi> in his Sermon <hi>in Natalem Domini,</hi> that as the Word was made fleſh, ſo our ſtony Hearts may be made fleſh alſo; that we might alwayes meditate on his Sacred Meſſage, and his. Heavenly Goſpell: <hi>Unto you this day is born, in the City of</hi> David, <hi>a Saviour which is Chriſt the Lord:</hi> For all our ſound comfort ſtands
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119631:51"/>in happineſſe, and all our happineſſe is in the Fellowſhip and Communion with God, and all our Fellowſhip and Communion with God, is by <hi>Jeſus. Christ,</hi> for ſo that good Divine St. <hi>John,</hi> tells us in his 1 Epiſt. cap. 2.3. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo, St. <hi>Austin</hi> uſeth a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent acclamation, to this purpoſe, in his ninth Sermon <hi>de Tempore,</hi> which as it is probable, he alſo preached on this day, <hi>ô beatum vagitum Infantuli be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ati,</hi> oh the bleſſed crying of a bleſſed babe, by which every faithfull ſervant and Son of God, eſcapeth eternal how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in Hell; <hi>ô ſplendidum &amp; Glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum praeſepe!</hi> Oh famous and glorious Manger, in which our Souls Manna lay! <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the bread of life that came down from Heaven, on which if a man once, &amp;c. <hi>ô quàm dites: ſunt panni tui!</hi> Oh how Rich and Honourable are the rags which have made plaiſters for our ſores, even for our ſins! I will ſhut up this paſſage with a Hymn of <hi>Prudentius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Mortale corpus ſumpſit immortalitas.</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t dum caducum poytat aeternus deus.</l>
                  <l>Tranſire nostrum poſſit ad coelestia.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119631:52"/>
               <p>And what ſay you now to theſe things before ſaid? Can they not yet perſwade you to yield, that it was the practiſe of Chriſtian Churches in Antient times to obſerve it? Yet put the caſe, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was not; you cannot, yea, I hope you will not deny, but it hath been the practiſe of theſe our Churches of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> I mean the Churches of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for divers Centuries, or hundreds of years to obſerve it; for they are both Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and reformed Churches, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unleſſe you mean by Chriſtian Churches, the old <hi>Browniſts</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> or the new <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Antipaedobaptists</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like proud and phantaſticall, and Phariſaicall Sectaries, and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts that are amongſt us, in theſe Giddy and unſetled times of ours, who think there is no true Chriſtian Church, but what is of their chooſing, planting, and erecting; who, like the <hi>Jews</hi> of old, cry <hi>Templum Domini,</hi> or like the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who will have no Church to be a true Church, but their Church at <hi>Rome;</hi> who ſtand upon their <hi>Pontificatibus,</hi> and are
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119631:52"/>all for the juſtification of their own O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, ſaying as thoſe <hi>Juſticiaries</hi> of old did, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.5. <hi>Stand by thy ſelf, or ſtand far off me, come not near me, for I am Holier then thou,</hi> &amp;c. And here I could tell you a thing (which perhaps alſo you are not ignorant of) that the late upſtart Seraphicall illuminated <hi>Independents,</hi> (as it is commonly thought) are likely to joſtle and thruſt the proud, rigid, Fantaſticall, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaicall <hi>Presbyterians</hi> out of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, even as they have cunningly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, and undermined the Reverend Biſhops, and their conformable Clergy out of theirs, <hi>neque enim lex juſtior ulla eſt, Quam necis artifices,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard nor read of any Chriſtian Churches, but have obſerved this day; and therefore howſoever ſuch factious and Schiſmaticall Wild-brain'd Zelots of our time, refuſe to do it, and both write and ſpeak againſt it, yet we know that all the Antient Fathers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, did celebrate it with great Solemnities, as Mr, <hi>Fiſher</hi> in his Vindication of our Goſpell Feſtivalls, hath wittily obſerved in his fifth Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even <hi>Cyprian, Baſil, Nazianzene,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119631:53"/>Ambroſe, Epiphanius, Jerome, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Fulgentius,</hi> alledging and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their very words, which they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on this day, and proving it withall, punctually plainly, and directly, that it was the 25th day of <hi>December</hi> that Chriſt was born on: And further, to confute your palpable Errour, he tells us there, That the Churches of <hi>Helvetia, Bohemia,
<note place="margin">Leye Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day a Sab. pag. 173. Dr. Rayn. Confer. with Hart. c. 8. S. 2.</note> Bremen, Auſpurg,</hi> the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Savoy, Poland, Hungary, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> do allow the Feaſts that belong to Chriſt, his Nativity, Circumciſion, Paſſion, &amp;c. The Churches of <hi>Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and all other <hi>Lutheran</hi>-Churches, do ſolemnly obſerve the Feaſt of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of Chriſt, and on that day uſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Hymns of Thankſgiving, made by <hi>Martin Luther</hi> himſelf;
<note place="margin">Perth. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed. pag. 85.</note> the Church of <hi>Geneva</hi> doth celebrate the day of his Nativity: wherefore (as he ſaith here for a Concluſion) ſeeing we are compaſſed about with ſo great a Cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, we muſt, according to the truth, affirm, That the Celebration of this Feaſt, is confirmed by the judgment of the Chriſtian Church in all ages. So we conclude againſt you, that your eleventh
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119631:53"/>Aſſertion is a meer falſhood, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt untruth, and no more to be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or believed, then that vain fancy, and fond ſurmiſe of yours, I mean the Fable and ſtory you tell us of in your <hi>Saints Rest,</hi> touching the raining down of <hi>Manna,</hi> on the Leads of the Church at <hi>Bridgnorth</hi> when you preached there: For ſome Gentlemen of worth in thoſe parts, have credibly reported it to be nothing elſe then the ſeeds of Hips and Hawes, being the excrements of Rooks and Jack-dawes, which they there had voyded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the Twelfth Argument.</head>
               <p>The twelfth Argument is this, <hi>In all doubtfull Caſes, a Wiſe man ought to go on the ſureſt ſide, and I am ſure it is no Sin not to keep it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, in this Allegation you ſeem to play the part of a Wiſe man; but in my Opinion you are onely wiſe in your own conceit; for my part, this I am ſure of; Firſt, in reſpect that <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day being the day of our Lords Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, is the Lords day,
<note place="margin">Cant. 4.9.</note> and by his ſpouſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119631:54"/>the Church is ſet a part to Gods publick worſhip, and our Souls edification, therefore it ought clearly to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med above any other of the common Week dayes. And for people on this day, willfully and contemptuouſly, to follow their ordinary (though at other times lawfull) vocations, or Callings, is in the firſt place, a breach of the fourth Commandement, for the day of Chriſts Nativity, is a Sabboth or Reſt to the Lord, and God will have us to keep ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Sabboth or Reſt-day. Next, it is a deſpiſing,
<note place="margin">Perk. caſes of Conſc. l. 1. c. 5. Sect. 5.</note> and diſhonouring of their Mother the Church, which, whoſoever are guilty of, not onely ſin againſt the fifth Commandment, but by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf, we are Injoyned to account all ſuch as Revolters from the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, Heathen men, and Publicans, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. Laſtly, it is a ground and inlet to the violation of all order and decency in Gods Service, which is expreſſely condemned in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and if to break Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> to contemn his Churches Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to become Heathens and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, and to overthrow all order and decency in Gods Services, be ſins and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119631:54"/>Offences to God; Then muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that not to keep this day, muſt needs be a ſin; and that to work, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our vocations on <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day, is a great and high offence, or indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty offered unto God, and his Church. And how then are you ſure it is no ſin not to keep it, but that your erronious Conſcience tells you ſo, and yet is it ſo nice and tender? on the other ſide you are not ſure, it is no ſin to keep it; this is the other part of your <hi>Dilemma,</hi> (for this is called in the Schools <hi>Syllogiſmus cornutus,</hi> or <hi>Syllogiſmus Crocodilinus</hi>) Well, <hi>ſat verbum Sapienti;</hi> If a word to the Wiſe may ſerve the turn, then will I anſwer you in a word: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you are perſwaded, and ſure in your ſtrong Conſcience, that it is no ſin not to keep it; yet we, on the other ſide, in our weak Conſciences, are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it is a ſin if we keep it not: And therefore if you remember, the Apoſtle's rule is, Let not the ſtronger Chriſtian deſpiſe the weaker,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.3, 4.</note> eſpecially in ſuch a Caſe as this, Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not, and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eateth, for God hath received him;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119631:55"/>Who art thou then that judgeſt another man's Servant? to his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth, yea he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him ſtand. One man eſteemeth one day above another, another eſteemeth every day alike. Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind; he that regardeth a day regardeth it unto the Lord, and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it: He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks: For none of us liveth to himſelf, and no man dyeth to himſelf, for the Kingdom of God is not Meat and Drink, but Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt; and he that in theſe things ſerveth <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is acceptable to God and approved of Men. Let us therefore follow after the the things which make for peace, and things wherewith we may edify another, for meat deſtroy not the work of God; all things indeed are pure, but it is evil for that man who eateth with Offence. It is good, neither to eat Fleſh, nor to drink Wine, nor any thing, whereby thy
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119631:55"/>Brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or is made weak; You ſee how wary the Apoſtle is, to adviſe us in and for things indifferent. not to be offended one with another, but to uſe all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian moderation and diſcretion, &amp; not to abuſe our Chriſtian Liberty, to the Scandal and Offence of our weak Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the thirteenth Argument.</head>
               <p>The thirteenth Argument is, <hi>That this day ought not to be celebrated becauſe there is more Sin committed in theſe</hi> 12 <hi>dayes than is in all the year following,</hi> viz. <hi>in Drunkenneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Oh Sir! This Argument and your laſt, are the leaſt and the weakeſt of them all, &amp; therefore I ſhal more eaſily anſwer them, &amp; briefly conclude. To this 13th I ſay as I did before, The Abuſe of a thing, that in it ſelf is lawful and good, cannot juſtly aboliſh or take away the lawful Uſe of it; For the beſt things that ever God created have been abuſed through Man's Corruption; even the whole
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119631:56"/>Creature is ſubject unto Vanity, that is, to Deſtruction, becauſe of Man's ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20. The holy Temple of our God hath been prophaned and defiled, and made a den of Theeves, and a Cage of unclean Birds, and a very Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Barbarous Souldiers Horſes to Lodge in, in theſe late uncivil Warrs; the holy Sabbath of our Lord hath been polluted, his Word and Sacraments abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Yea, becauſe the Scriptures are in ſome places ſomewhat hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ood, therefore thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable, do wreſt them and perven them to their own Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.16. And becauſe of this, muſt the Scriptures be rejected, and not peruſed? Becauſe the good Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God are abuſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wicked Miſcreants, therefore muſt the Creatures be refuſed, ſeeing every Creature of God is good, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be refuſed,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.4.</note> eſpecially if it be received with thankfulneſs: for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed unto us by the Word of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prayer. The like may be ſaid of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sanctuary of our God, of the Sab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Sacraments; for unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> things are pure; but unto
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119631:56"/>them that are defiled and unbelieving, is nothing pure, but even their minds and conſciences are defiled, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>But you affirm, and that peremptorily, that there is more ſinne committed in theſe Twelve Days, than in all the year after, in Drunkenneſs and Gluttony: And how are you ſure of this? for it is impoſſible that you ſhould prove this to be true. Can God be more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in Twelve Days, than in twelve Moneths? Although a bare Denyall might ſerve here for a ſufficient anſwer: yet put the caſe that many men, being at this time apt and addicted, <hi>genio ſuo indulgere,</hi> to give way to their unbride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led luſts, and diſordered affections, in the free uſe of God's Creatures, ſhould be exceſſive in their Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo exorbitant and extravagant in other vain Recreations, and idle Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings and Paſtimes, that God may hereby be ſomewhat diſhonoured, and this bleſſed time of his Son's Nativity abuſed, men a little forgetting the right and proper End wherfore at firſt it was inſtituted and ordained: Yet conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many good, and gracious, and bountifull Deeds, that heretofore have
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119631:57"/>been done at this time, the gallant Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality, the free and generous Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, by our worthy, noble, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Gentlemen, and our rich, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, able, and ſufficient Yeomen, by relieving the Poor, helping Widows and Fatherleſs Children, cloathing the Naked, feeding the Hungry, viſiting the Sick, and thoſe that were in Priſons. Take but a Ballance, or a pair of Scales, and lay theſe many good Almſ-Deeds and Works of Piety and Charity in one Scale, and put the Evil Deeds that have been committed in the other Scale, and I dare ſay the good deeds ſhall out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh the bad,
<note place="margin">Zac. 5.7.</note> though they be as heavy as <hi>maſſa plumbi,</hi> a Talent of Lead. And this which I have here written, hath more probability and likelyhood of truth in it, than that which you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, in ſaying there is more ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in theſe Twelve Days, than in all the year after. But you had ſpoken more properly and truly, if you had ſaid, There are more good Deeds done by ſome good minded and charitably diſpoſed Chriſtians, in theſe Twelve Days, than in all the year after. Yours is a falſe aſſertion, and a groſs abſur'd
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119631:57"/>aſſeveration: and I verily think, that you vent it to skar and deterr men from keeping any Chriſtmas at all, becauſe ſome ignorant, diſſolute, and deboiſt Fellows do ſpend this time idely and vainly in exceſſive eating and drinking, ryoting and revelling, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But our pious Anceſtors, of famous memory, were ſo addicted and devoted to the Reverence, and religious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this Time, that they ſpent it in a ſober, civil, and careful manner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thankful to God, and rejoycing in the Lord, for that ineffable and inaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Benefit and Bleſſing which he beſtowed upon the World at this time; and therefore they were willing and contented, freely and cheerfully to part with their goods, and impart them to the poor, in plentifull manner: And this they did for his ſake alone, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich, for their ſakes became poor, that ſo they, through his Poverty, might be made rich, as the Apoſtle elegantly expreſſeth it, and ſetteth forth the Grace of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in a moſt ſweet, and gracious, and glorious manner, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. But where is our Bounty, or our Benificence? Where
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119631:58"/>is our Charity, Liberality, and Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in theſe cold degenerate and Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate times? That witty Saying may here be verified, How that one handful of old Friendſhip, is better than an an armful of new Courteſy; For all our Love and Charity, in theſe daies, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into nothing elſe but meer verball and external Complement, ſo true is that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. Men in theſe daies profeſs that they know God, but by their works they deny him, and therefore they are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and diſobedient, and to every good work, reprobate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer to the fourteenth Argument.</head>
               <p>The fourteenth is this, <hi>God bleſſeth His own day, the Sabbath, but hath not bleſſed this with ſucceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Int his your <hi>ultimum Refugium,</hi> you think you have paid it home, and bitt the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nail on the head: But, Good Sir, What could you ſay, If any man ſhould ask you, Why God hath not bleſſed this day? For it hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that this day is aequal and aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119631:58"/>with the Sabbath; and if he hath bleſſed the one, ſo queſtionleſs he hath bleſſed the other, and ſanctifyed it, and ſet it apart, for a holy Convocation, and thankful Commemoration, of the Birth and Nativity of his onely begotten Son; and that in the 118 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> may fitly and properly be applyed unto it, <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made,</hi> (i. e.) which the Lord hath magnifyed, and advanced, and fingled out, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, for a more peculiar end and purpoſe than other ordinary daies of the year are; And this Interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of the Word, that place in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.5, 6. doth well approve of, and allow it: This is then the day which the Lord hath made; yea, this is the day wherein the Lord Himſelf was made, ſaith <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus.</hi> Therefore we will rejoyce and be glad in it; <hi>Fear not</hi> (ſaid the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> to thoſe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds of <hi>Bethlehem), for behold I bring you good tidings of great joy;</hi> ſo that here good Tidings do attend it, and great Joy doth accompany it, which ſhall be unto all People: for unto you is born this day, in the City of <hi>David,</hi> a Saviour, which is <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Lord.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119631:59"/>And that the Lord hath bleſſed this day with ſucceſs, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, and their harmonious and unanimous conſents, ſhall bear me witneſs. Firſt, That Evangelical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſyes of it, ſaying, Unto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given; <hi>Datus ex Divinitate, natus ex Virgine,</hi> ſaith <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus</hi> on the words, excellently; In that he is ſaid to be born, it betokens his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; in that he is ſaid to be given, it ſignifies his Divine Nature: The Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical. Union of both doth make one and the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>one Immanuel,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>God with us: The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is upon his ſhoulder, his Name ſhall be called Wonderfull, Counſellor, the Mighty God, the Everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace; the Increaſe of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Peace ſhall have none End, he ſhall ſit upon the Throne of</hi> David, <hi>and upon his. Kingdom, to order it, and to eſtabliſh it, with Judgment and with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, from henceforth even for ever:</hi> The z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this, (i.e.) his ſingular Love and Care for his Elect ſhall effect it. And doth not God bleſſe this day then with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119631:59"/>ſncceſſe? and doth not the Princely Prophet <hi>David</hi> alſo ſing of this Alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and chant it to the Tune of his Harp and Viol, and ſet forth the happy and proſperous ſucceſſe of this Day, and the flouriſhing Eſtate of the Church, by the Kingdom, and coming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Fleſh? <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand untill I make thine Enemies tpy Foot: ſtool,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.44. we find that <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf giveth the Interpretation hereof, and ſheweth that this cannot be properly applied un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>David,</hi> but to Himſelf; and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the words that follow in that Pſalm,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſhall ſend the Rod of thy Power out of Zion. For out of Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath God appeared in perfect Beauty,</hi> Pſal. 50.2. And from thence, this Rod and this Power of his ſhall ſtreth forth it ſelf throughout all the World; and this Power chiefly conſiſteth and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Preaching of his Word; and by this Rod, and by this Scepter of thy Kingdom, which is a right Scepter, be thou Ruler in the middeſt of thine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; thy People ſhall come willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the time of aſſembling thine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in holy beauty, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> by thy Word,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119631:60"/>thy People ſhall be aſſembled into thy Church; whoſe Increaſe ſhall be ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undant, ſo plentiful, and ſo wonderful as the drops of the Dew of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; For it is ſaid, <hi>The Youth of thy Womb ſhall be as the Morning Dew,</hi> or (as the ordinary Reading of the Pſalm is), <hi>In the Day of thy Power ſhall they offer thee Free-will-Offerings with a Holy Worſhip; the Dew of thy Birth is of the Womb of the Morning.</hi> Which howſoever ſome Interpret it of the Birth of Chriſt, yet <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> do underſtand it to be <hi>innumera illa multitudo electorum quae comparebit in eccleſia tanquam ſtillans ros à coele, &amp; ſub auroram depluens,</hi> That innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble multitude of the Elect, which ſhall be as viſible and apparent, and as abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in the Church, as the dew which diſtilleth from Heaven, and lyeth on the face of the Earth in the morning; as we know the Elect elſe-where in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are compared to the Starrs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22.17</note> and to the ſand which is upon the Sea-ſhore for multitude; the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> hath alſo foretold of theſe things, ſpeaking of the peace, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and glory of the Church of God,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119631:60"/>that ſhould be by the Kingdome and coming of Chriſt: Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, ſaith he, <hi>Yet a little while, and I will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth, and the Sea, and the dry Land; and I will move all Nations, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of all Nations ſhall come, and I will fill this Houſe with Glory, ſaith the Lord of Hosts. The deſire of all Nations ſhall come;</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for in Him are all things that can be deſired, and all Nations ought to look for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Him; and therefore in this ſenſe He is called <hi>Rex gentium,</hi> the King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe all Nations ought not onely to ſeek and deſire Him,
<note place="margin">Jer. 10.7.</note> but alſo to ſerve Him and obey Him: And doth not alſo the Prophet <hi>Zachariah</hi> ſay as much? For he propheſied much about the time as <hi>Haggai</hi> did, and was ſent of the Lord to help him in the labour, and to confirm the ſame Doctrine, even when the time of the 70 years Captivity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> was expired; and he paralleleth or compareth that time of their deliverance from Captivity, to this happy time of our ſpiritual delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the thraldome and Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of Sin and Sathan; ſaying, Zach.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119631:61"/>9.9. <hi>Kejoyce greatly O Daughter of</hi> Zion; <hi>ſhout for joy O Daughter of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; <hi>Behold, Thy King cometh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; He is juſt, and having Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; He is meek and lowly, Riding upon an Aſſe, and upon a Colt the foal of an Aſſe. And I will cut off the Chariot from</hi> Ephraim, <hi>and the Horſe from</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>and the Battle-bow ſhall be cut off; and He ſhall ſpeak peace unto the Heathen, and His Dominion ſhall be from Sea even to Sea, and from the River</hi> (i. e. from the River <hi>Euphrates) even to the Ends of the Earth.</hi> Here is ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs enough, if we obſerve it; for His Dominion ſhall be from Sea to Sea, that is, from the Red Sea, to the Sea called <hi>Syriacum:</hi> and by theſe places, which the Jews knew well enough, he meant an infinite ſpace and compaſs over the whole World. As for Thee alſo, (<hi>i. e.</hi> as for Thee Oh Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> and Daughter <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) by the blood of my Covenant, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the blood of Chriſt, Thou ſhalt be ſaved; and by this blood I have looſed, or I have ſent forth the Priſoners out of the pit, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) not the pit of purgatory, or <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> as the Papiſts would have it underſtood;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119631:61"/>but out of the bottomleſs pit of Hell, wherein there is no water; (<hi>i. e.</hi>) no Comfort, no Cooling, no refreſhing at all, for they that are there, are alwayes ſcorched and tormented in theſe infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, eternal, and unquenchable flames without any hope of eaſe or end at all, as it may appear by the confeſſion of <hi>Dives;</hi> Turn ye then to the ſtrong hold, ye Priſoners of hope, even to Day do I declare that I will render double unto Thee; that is, double Benefit, and proſperity in reſpect of that which your Fathers enjoyed, from <hi>David</hi>'s time to the Captivity, as ſome Interp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the place; or, as others think, by double in that place, may well be underſtood a double deliverance; not onely a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Corporal, but a Spiritual and Eternal deliverance; no onely a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from 400 years bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 7.6.</note> or from 70 years Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> but from the everlaſting bondage, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and Thraldome of Sin and Sarban. Wherefore comfort ye my People, doth your God ſay by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.1.</note> Speak ye comfortably to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and cry unto Her, that Her warfare is accompliſhed,</hi> (i. e.) That
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119631:62"/>the time of Her affliction is ended, and that Her iniquity is pardoned, for She hath received of the Lord's hand dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for all her ſins, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) as ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it ſufficient correction for all Her ſins, inſinuating that the Lord will afflict his People no more ſo long, or ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe his Loving-kindneſs hath overcome his heavy diſpleaſure; ſo ſaith <hi>Jerome</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> the word [dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble] ought to be taken for enough, or full, as it is uſed by the ſame Prophet, or as ſome interpret it,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 61.7.</note> double grace for double grief; as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble puniſhment, one in her Soul, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in her Body; ſo now, ſhe ſhall have by Chriſt a double bleſſing, <hi>vix.</hi> in this World Collation of grace, and in the World to come poſſeſſion of glory: or a double favour; Firſt, in that her travail is ended; Secondly, For that her ſin is pardoned: or double, that is, as <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus</hi> and <hi>Arcularius</hi> expound it, many benefits, a certain number being put for an uncertain, (which is an uſuall Hebraiſm in the old Teſtament,) for the ſufferings of Chriſt are a ſufficient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for all her ſins,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.2.</note> and for the ſins of the whole World: yea, where
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119631:62"/>ſin abounded, there grace ſuper-aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſaith <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 5.20. For, that place in <hi>Eſay</hi> before alleadged, is, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect propheſie concerning the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, and the happy ſucceſs of this Day, as both <hi>Muſculus</hi> and <hi>Hyperius</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> do expound it; and the coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh (you know) is the conſolation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and comfort of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (for ſo it is called, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25.) and this comfort the God of all comfort will have proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the mouth of all his Prophets and Preachers, which have bin ſince the World began, and ſo we find in holy Writ, that he ſtirred up <hi>Daniel, Haggai, Malachi, Zachariah, Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and other; (untill the coming of Chriſt himſelf) who did alwayes exhort his People, to be of good chear, and to be of good comfort in the midſt of all their afflictions and tribulations, and ſtill to hope againſt hope, as our Father <hi>Abraham</hi> did:
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> So <hi>Zacharias,</hi> in his Hymn, openeth his mouth, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for he hath Viſited and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed his People, rayſing up the horn of Salvation unto us, as he ſpeak by the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119631:63"/>mouth of all his Prophets, which have been ſince the World began;</hi> So St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his Sermon, <hi>ad populum,</hi> all the Prophets from <hi>Samuel,</hi> and thenceforth, as many have ſpoken, have likewiſe foretold of theſe dayes; and to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> that pious and famous Captain of <hi>Caſarea, Acts</hi> 10.43. To him give all the Prophets witneſs, <hi>That through his Name, all that believe in Him ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins:</hi> Now with what face can any man ſay, That God hath not bleſſed this Day with ſucceſſe, ſeeing this Day hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo many good &amp; gracious effects, glorious wonders, and theſe not only in the Earth, but alſo in the Heavens; for if we will believe <hi>Venerable Beda,</hi> it was ſo, <hi>nato Domino, ſtellae dederunt lumen in Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>todiis, &amp; laetatae ſunt; plus nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> luxêrrent ei cum Jocunditate, qui fecit illas, quaſi ſign is ſic conclamantes, Hic eſt domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus noſter &amp; non aeſtimabitur alius:</hi> The Staris at His Birth did ſhine more clearly and chearfully then their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom was; becauſe their Maker was then born, ſeeming to tell us; This is the Lord our God, and we muſt look for none other. Here me-thinks, alluding to that excellent ſaying in <hi>Job,</hi> I cannot chuſe but argue and inferr upon it; Did
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119631:63"/>the Starrs of the morning praiſe him, the wiſe men of the Eaſt rejoyce, and ſo the Shepheards, and all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the Angels rejoyce and ſing? Job 38.7. <hi>And why then ſhall we be dumb and ſilent? and not break forth into the like Exultation, Jubilation, and Rejoycing?</hi> And have we not a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſo to do, Pſal. 33.1. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, Oye Righteous, for it becometh well the just to be thankful; Rejoyce in the Lord alwayes, and again I ſay Rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 4.4. <hi>Yea, let the heart of all them rejoyce that ſerve the Lord.</hi> Let us then here a little correct our Selves and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect our Spirits, as thoſe four leprous men did, who returned from the ſpoyl of the <hi>Syrian</hi>-Camp; and ſay, We do not well, This Day is a Day of good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and ſhould we hold our peace? For mine own part, let the Leproſie of thoſe men cleave unto my skin, if it be not as joyful a thing to me to record, and recount, to commemorate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate the honour and happineſſe, and good ſucceſs of this Day, as ever it was to them to carry the happy news of the flight of <hi>Aram:</hi> Rejoyce then O ye Heavens, and be glad O Earth, for
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119631:64"/>on this Day Heaven and Earth were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and God was made Man to make peace between God and Man: Rejoyce, O Grandfather <hi>Adam,</hi> for on this Day, that firſt promiſe made unto thee concerning Chriſt, began to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>How that the ſeed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpents head,</hi> Gen. 3.15. Rejoyce, father <hi>Abraham; for on this Day in thy Seed All the Nations of the Earth are bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 22.18. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, King <hi>David;</hi> for on this Day God hath of the fruit of thy Body, ſet a King upon thy Throne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.11. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, ye Prophets of the Lord; for all your prophecyes on this Day were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Rejoyce ye that are ſick, for on this Day the Phyſitian of the World was borne. <hi>Venit de coelo magnus Medicus, Qui per totom ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Jacebat agrotus,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Austin.</hi> Rejoyce ye Virgins, for a Virgin on this Day brought forth a Son: Rejoyce ye Children, for on this Day the great God became a little Babe: Let all People, Jews, and Gentiles; Bond and Free; High and Low; Rich and Poor, one with another: Let all rejoyce together, for that He who was in the beginning without any
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119631:64"/>beginning; for He is that true Melche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedeck, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>having neither beginning of Dayes, nor end of Life,</hi> Heb. 7.3. And therefore in this ſenſe is Styled an everlaſting Father,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> becauſe he is the Author of eternity to all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for that He who was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, before all beginnings, and in a time when there was no time meaſured or limited out,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> yet in the fulneſs of time was made of a Woman, and wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Swadling-Clothes; for that He who <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> the Word became <hi>Infans in cunis vagiens,</hi> an Infant not able to ſpeak one ſyllable; ſo that He, who was God, did vouchſafe to become <hi>Deus nobiſcum,</hi> God with us; yea, and to dwell amongſt us, appearing in the ſhape of a Man; for as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellently expreſſeth both his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and exaltation, thus ſaying,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſe ſeſe exinanivit</hi> (i. e.) as <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoundeth it, <hi>Quaſi ex omni ſeipſum ad nihil redegit,</hi> (i. e.) He that at firſt made all things of nothing, did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards make nothing of Himſelf for Man's ſake, He made Himſelf of no Reputation, and took upon Him the form of a Servant, and was made in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119631:65"/>likeneſs of a Man; and being found in faſhion of a Man, he humbled Himſelf, and became obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs: Wherefore God alſo hath highly exalted Him, and given Him a Name which is above eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Name, That at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, of things in Earth, and of things under the Earth: and that every tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord to the glory of God the Father. To which God the Father, and God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, three in one, and one in three; one immortall, inviſible, indiviſible, incomprehenſible, and one onely ever wiſe God; be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and aſcribed (as of due belongeth) all Honour and Glory, Power, and Praiſe, and Obedience, both now and for ever more Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
